<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A reply to that pernicious and scandalous libel, lately printed in Holland, in an almanack, for the year 1687 Written by (whom?) but Jo. Partridge an English renegado. Manifesting his horrid treasons, wicked blasphemies, and most absurd errours in art; and exhibiting the genuine signification of the stars toward Great Britain. Published by authority.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 166KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91663</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895339</idno>
  <idno type="VID">152706</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248567362</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1065</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229656</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895339</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99895339e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91663)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152706)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2317:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A reply to that pernicious and scandalous libel, lately printed in Holland, in an almanack, for the year 1687 Written by (whom?) but Jo. Partridge an English renegado. Manifesting his horrid treasons, wicked blasphemies, and most absurd errours in art; and exhibiting the genuine signification of the stars toward Great Britain. Published by authority.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 49, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Nath. Thompson, at the entrance into the Old Spring-Garden,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Partridge, John, 1644-1715 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Almanacs, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152706:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152706:1"/>
            <p>A REPLY TO That Pernicious and scandalous LIBEL, lately Printed in <hi>HOLLAND,</hi> IN AN ALMANACK, For the Year 1687.</p>
            <p>Writted by (whom?) but <hi>Io. Partridge</hi> an <hi>English <hi>Renegado.</hi>
               </hi> Manifesting his horrid <hi>Treasons,</hi> wicked <hi>Blasphemies,</hi> and most absurd Errours in <hi>Art;</hi> and exhibiting the genuine signification of the STARS toward GREAT BRITAIN.</p>
            <q>What reward shall be given (or done) unto thee thou false Tongue; even mighty and sharp Arrows with hot burning Coles. <bibl>
                  <hi>Psal. 120.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Let the mischief of their own Lips fall upon the head of them: Let hot burning Coles fall upon them: Let them be cast into the Fire, and into the Pit, that they never rise up again. <bibl>
                  <hi>Psal. 140.9 10.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>If ye do Live, ye shall be Accursed: If ye Die, the Cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>se shall be your Portion. <bibl>
                  <hi>Eccles. 41.9</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Published by Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Nath. Thompson,</hi> at the Entrance into the <hi>Old Spring-Garden,</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:152706:2"/>
            <head>TO ALL LOYAL READERS, WHETHER <hi>ENGLISH,</hi> or <hi>DUTCH,</hi> Or, of any other NATION.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOu may wonder to see a <hi>Prognostication</hi> for <hi>1687.</hi> peep out in <hi>August,</hi> viz. when more than half the Year's expir'd. But you'l admire much more at the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion, when, in the Reading it you find 'tis a <hi>Reply</hi> to <hi>One</hi> of the same Year, written (I am asham'd to speak it) by an <hi>English-Man,</hi> with a design to <hi>Traduce</hi> and <hi>Trample</hi> upon His <hi>Majesty,</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> to decry <hi>Monarchy,</hi> vent <hi>Treason,</hi> with <hi>Blasphemy,</hi> and all manner of wickedness that can be exprest in <hi>Ink</hi> and <hi>Paper;</hi> And this under pretence of <hi>Astrology,</hi> to the great dishonour of <hi>God,</hi> and the Science of the Stars, bidding de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance to Heaven it self, with the greatest impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and indecency of Expression, that possibly can proceed from the Pen of one in <hi>Humane</hi> shape.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:152706:2"/>
            <p>But that which we may most marvel at, is, that this <hi>Author,</hi> (fled for <hi>Treason</hi> into <hi>Holland,</hi> should There find Protection. In <hi>Holland!</hi> I say, a Country in Amity with <hi>England,</hi> and Ally'd to His <hi>Majesty</hi> by the strongest and most <hi>Royal</hi> of all <hi>Pledges,</hi> that Nature or Nations can afford: I mean the happy <hi>Espousal</hi> of the Royal and Illustrious Princess, the <hi>Princess MARY,</hi> the Eldest Daughter of <hi>England,</hi> unto the thrice Noble, Valiant, and Magnanimous <hi>Prince of Orange:</hi> The present visible hopes of that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustrious and Fortunate Nations Rise, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. If, I say, this be consider'd by that <hi>Wise</hi> and <hi>Prudent</hi> People, they'l never believe it <hi>Pleasant,</hi> or <hi>Grateful</hi> to the <hi>Ears</hi> of that <hi>Royal Princess,</hi> or to the most Excellent <hi>Prince</hi> Her Husband. Nor is it for the Honour of the High and Mighty <hi>States</hi> themselves, to suffer this bold <hi>Libeller</hi> to Publish his impudent <hi>Scandals</hi> and <hi>Treasons</hi> (un-regarded) under their very <hi>Noses.</hi> Which practice tends, not only to the dishonour and disturbance of those against whom he levels his Arrows of Envy; but, to a direct breach of the Friendship of both <hi>Nations:</hi> For the continuance whereof, every good Man in each Country will always Pray.</p>
            <p>If a <hi>Letter</hi> or <hi>False Report</hi> have (formerly) set <hi>Nations at odds,</hi> what then may be the Issue of a <hi>Connivance</hi> at the grosest <hi>Scandals</hi> and <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons?</hi> and wherein the greatest of <hi>Kings,</hi> and the
<pb facs="tcp:152706:3"/> best and most Antient of <hi>Religions</hi> is concern'd? I will not presume to Augure, or Determine, what: But this I may be bold to affirm, if <hi>Honour</hi> be tender in a <hi>single Person,</hi> 'tis much more so in a <hi>Prince,</hi> or <hi>Nation</hi> If the <hi>Faith of Nations</hi> be allow'd <hi>Sacred,</hi> then, why not their Honour? It concerns me, that I am constrain'd to re-mind my Native Country of th se broad fac'd <hi>Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,</hi> thus <hi>(sine causa)</hi> cast upon Her: But more, that in all this time there has not been found one <hi>Loyal English-Man</hi> of Courage and Ability to Retort them.</p>
            <p>As for the method, I have follow'd the <hi>Libeller,</hi> almost <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (save in his rude and ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Poetry, at the beginning, and end of his Libel, the substance whereof is sufficiently reply'd unto in the following discourse.) I have ript up his Ridiculous <hi>Follies</hi> expos'd his <hi>Blasphemies</hi> and <hi>Treasons,</hi> Corrected his <hi>Errours</hi> in <hi>Art,</hi> made known his gross <hi>Juglings</hi> and the no-ground he had, wherein to <hi>Traduce</hi> his <hi>KING</hi> and <hi>Country.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Hexameters over the Months, I will not call them so much an <hi>Answer</hi> to his Infamous <hi>Rhimes,</hi> as Direction, and Caution to him of the danger of jesting with <hi>Edge-Tools,</hi> least his Treasonable and Blasphemous Mirth bring him to Perd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ion. <hi>Non bonum est ludere cum Sanctis.</hi> Had I exactly follow'd him here, I must have put my self upon the ungrateful <hi>Drudgery</hi> of repeating
<pb facs="tcp:152706:3"/> all his <hi>Atheisme</hi> and <hi>Blasphemies;</hi> which must needs Nauseate any sober <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have Explain'd all the horrid <hi>Scandals</hi> and <hi>Falshoods</hi> contain'd in his <hi>Chronology,</hi> and have taken the pains to inform him of some things, he'l no more thank me for, than care to hear of.</p>
            <p>Now that <hi>Truth</hi> may Triumph, and <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Falshood</hi> meet its just <hi>Reward;</hi> That our N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble Nation, and the most Puissant <hi>Governour</hi> thereof, may ever (as they already do) <hi>out-shine,</hi> and <hi>dazle</hi> their <hi>Enemies,</hi> and see the <hi>Down-fall</hi> of such as wish them <hi>Ill.</hi> That they may be the <hi>wonder</hi> of the <hi>World</hi> in their <hi>Devotion</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> and true <hi>Loyalty</hi> towards the <hi>King.</hi> That all true and useful <hi>Arts</hi> may Flourish among us; and that Loyal <hi>Artists</hi> may prove as Zealous in the Ʋse of them, for the Honour and Advantage of the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> as <hi>Rebels</hi> and <hi>Traytors</hi> are ready to imploy them against both. Is the constant Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>(Gentlemen!)</salute>
               <signed>Your Humble Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="observations">
            <pb facs="tcp:152706:4"/>
            <div n="January" type="month">
               <head>Observations on JANUARY.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>Touch'd with the sense of Ancient <hi>Britains</hi> worth,</l>
                     <l>My Pent-up <hi>Muse</hi> into a <hi>Flame</hi> breaks forth,</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Sacred Fury!</hi> scorns to be afraid,</l>
                     <l>Of vaunting Boasts dull <hi>Hereticks</hi> have made,</l>
                     <l>Against the <hi>Christian Truth</hi> which must prevail;</l>
                     <l>While every <hi>Schism</hi> unto <hi>Her</hi> strike Sail.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <hi>REader!</hi> That thou may'st see what an <hi>English<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> the <hi>Libeller</hi> is, he hath omitted the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom</hi> of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. in his Calendar, which was <hi>January</hi> 30, 1648. a <hi>dismal Day</hi> indeed! and never to be forgotten by any Loyal Man, and Christian. A Day commanded by <hi>Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to be observ'd for ever. But the <hi>Libeller</hi> is as much a Friend to the <hi>Priviledges</hi> of <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> as to the <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Prerogative</hi> of Kings. <hi>i. e.</hi> For either, or neither, as his perishing <hi>Interest</hi> leads him. For his <hi>Astrological judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of this Month, as they are not many, nor Material, so had he no great ground in <hi>Art,</hi> whereon to raise any. Howbeit, he makes <hi>Soldiers</hi> brisk and busie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in this un-active and un-sutable time of the Year: Whenas, his <hi>Tusser</hi> might have taught him better. <hi>Astrology</hi> tells him, that every Coelestial <hi>Agent</hi> works upon the <hi>Patient; secundum quid, i▪ e.</hi> according to its <hi>aptness</hi> and <hi>disposition</hi> to receive the influence and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression; and to the <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Place</hi> also, when, and where the <hi>effect</hi> is expected; according to <hi>Hipocrates.</hi> Now <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary,</hi> of all the Months in the Year, is the most unfit for <hi>Martial</hi> business, or briskness. And I will inform the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beller, That though the Loadstone will draw Iron, it will not draw a Nail out of a Post.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="February" type="month">
               <pb facs="tcp:152706:4"/>
               <head>Observations on FEBRUARY.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>Right <hi>Christian Priests</hi> are like their <hi>Mother,</hi> True,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pious</hi> and <hi>Painful,</hi> and <hi>Obedient</hi> too.</l>
                     <l>Their <hi>Charity's</hi> so great, as fain would Save</l>
                     <l>The veriest <hi>Villain,</hi> and the vilest <hi>Knave:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Even such as <hi>Wrong</hi> them most! This is their <hi>Care,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To bring <hi>Truths Enemies</hi> to Bliss by <hi>Prayer.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>HEre the <hi>Libeller</hi> boldly Praedicts— <hi>Some high offers made to the King of</hi> Spain <hi>by some Grave Saturnine States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi> He seems to build his Judgement upon the <hi>Sextile</hi> of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn</hi> and <hi>Mars;</hi> And so makes <hi>Mars</hi> to signifie that <hi>Monarch.</hi> But if any demand, <hi>Quo Warranto,</hi> by what Authority he doth so? He hath nothing to Answer. For neither is <hi>Spain</hi> it self, or yet that <hi>Catholick Prince,</hi> signified under <hi>Mars.</hi> And if he subject that <hi>Monarch</hi> to <hi>Saturn,</hi> (as some <hi>Astrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> do, and perhaps, truly) then he makes <hi>Mars</hi> the <hi>Grave States-man,</hi> who is to propound these offers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, <hi>Primae impressionis,</hi> the very first time that <hi>Mars</hi> hath been term'd a <hi>Grave States-man:</hi> Nor was he ever esteem'd a <hi>Politician,</hi> except in the <hi>Libellers Astrology;</hi> who, it seems, hath got <hi>Caucus</hi>'s Art, and can make (—<hi>Candida de nigris, &amp; de candentibus atra) Saturne,</hi> the <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aring Boy,</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> the Sober Thinking <hi>Philosopher.</hi>— He goes on, The <hi>Conjunction of</hi> Jupiter <hi>and</hi> Mars <hi>in</hi> Sagitary, <hi>disturbs the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy in</hi> England; <hi>I hope,</hi> (saith he) <hi>They are not about to put on</hi> Buff-Coats; <hi>if they do, the</hi> Souldier <hi>must wear the</hi> Black Ones. But, blessed be God, we have heard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f no such Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siastical War in <hi>England.</hi> And to say the Truth, his Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction is without ground; For, if <hi>Cancer</hi> be the present <hi>Horoscope</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> (as it is,) then are the <hi>Clergy</hi> thereof not under <hi>Sagitary,</hi> but <hi>Aquarius;</hi> and may <hi>wear their Black Gowns</hi> themselves, if they <hi>Forfeit</hi> them not, or make themselves <hi>Irregular,</hi> by Dancing after the <hi>LIBELLERS</hi> Pipe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="March" type="month">
               <pb facs="tcp:152706:5"/>
               <head>Observations on MARCH.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>This <hi>Papal-Power,</hi> though <hi>Envy'd</hi> by the <hi>Fiend,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Is That will bring His <hi>Kingdom</hi> to an <hi>End,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That <hi>Fiend!</hi> which s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ts his <hi>Sons</hi> a broaching <hi>Lyes,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To <hi>Cheat</hi> the <hi>Easy,</hi> and to <hi>Damn</hi> the <hi>Wise.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Our <hi>Saviour's</hi> Promise to his <hi>Church</hi> is sure▪</l>
                     <l>With <hi>IT</hi> He'll be, while <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon</hi> endure.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <hi>MArch,</hi> is threat'ned by the <hi>Libeller, to be a Month of Action with a Witnes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> And to bode <hi>an Earth-quake among Gown-men, both Sacred and Secular; Bishops, Judges Civilians,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>are blown up, and out of their Elements</hi> — But not one word of all this h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th <hi>proved true.</hi> Nor was it likely it should. For let us examine upon what <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figuration</hi> he lays the weight of this <hi>Praediction;</hi> and we find it to be upon the <hi>Quadrate</hi> of the <hi>Luminaries</hi> to <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi> at the <hi>New Moon.</hi> But doth not every <hi>Astrologer</hi> know that <hi>Qudrates</hi> are <hi>Aspects</hi> but of imperfect <hi>Enmity</hi> at the most? And that <hi>Jupiter</hi> is a Star of an Amicable and Preserving <hi>Influence</hi> Naturally? And are we not taught by the <hi>Sages</hi> of this <hi>Science,</hi> that if that good Planet hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to be detrimented, (which here he is not) it doth only <hi>minuere, (i. e.)</hi> Lessen his benefique <hi>Energie,</hi> but not <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mute</hi> his Nature? How then, I say, should such an <hi>Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake</hi> have fallen out?— But the <hi>event</hi> hath answer'd his <hi>Prediction;</hi> As there was no ground for it, so nothing like it hath happen'd. The <hi>Libeller</hi> is as true in what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, <hi>viz, About the third and fourth day a Surprize of some Town, Castle, Fort,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Holland</hi> threat'ned with <hi>War,</hi> and <hi>Denmark</hi> with <hi>Invasion, England</hi> and <hi>France</hi> with <hi>Discontents,</hi> &amp;c. All which have been fulfil'd <hi>per</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to the Lying <hi>Libellers</hi> Credit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="April" type="month">
               <pb facs="tcp:152706:5"/>
               <head>Observations on APRIL.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Reason</hi> must yield to <hi>Faith</hi> in Sacred things;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Priests,</hi> like good <hi>Angels,</hi> still good Tidings bring.</l>
                     <l>'Tis for our <hi>Souls</hi> they <hi>Watch.</hi> We then should <hi>Pray</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>For, not <hi>Traduce</hi> them: least we run <hi>Astray</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>From the great Shepherds <hi>Fold.</hi> Ungrateful men,</l>
                     <l>Do <hi>Crucifie</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>Life</hi> agen.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THe Libeller confidently tells us,— <hi>This is a month of War too, with News of a Bloody Dispute by Sea or Land, or both—</hi> But, for his <hi>Conviction</hi> there was not one word of any <hi>War,</hi> or any such <hi>Bloody Dispute</hi> heard of in all this <hi>month.</hi> And yet herewith he hath threat'ned <hi>England, France, Scotland, Holland, Denmark, Sweden,</hi> and part of <hi>Germany.</hi>— The Man's chief design is to <hi>Terrifie</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with <hi>War, Disturbances,</hi> &amp;c. but is hitherto mistaken in his measures, as he is like to be for the Future; Maugre all his <hi>Fanatick</hi> malice. For the <hi>Zodiacal Square</hi> of <hi>Mars</hi> to the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon,</hi> (he lays so much stress on) is se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated, even beyond the <hi>Orbs</hi> of <hi>Mars,</hi> and <hi>They</hi> much <hi>swif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> in motion than <hi>He.</hi> Which had the <hi>Libeller</hi> minded, he had not been guilty of this Foolish and Ridiculous <hi>menace.</hi> Well! but though he hath frighted us with false fears of Variety of Mischiefs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet he says, <hi>The</hi> Trine <hi>of the</hi> Sun <hi>and</hi> Jupiter <hi>from</hi> Sagitary <hi>and</hi> Aries, <hi>prefers some very Loyal Red Letter'd-Clergy-man, Common Lawyer, or Civilian, and that in</hi> England <hi>too.</hi> The Libeller is here turn'd <hi>Parasite,</hi> and <hi>Fawns</hi> upon, and <hi>Flatters</hi> those whom he mortally <hi>hates.</hi> Or else it may be he hath some Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals of a <hi>Penitent Conscience</hi> (which I wish him most heartily, if he have not) otherwise, how can we think him in earnest, when he allows of a <hi>Red-letter'd-man</hi> to be Loyal? Let him <hi>Read</hi> this <hi>Lecture</hi> to those <hi>Gontlemen,</hi> who in their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <hi>Sermons,</hi> (and in Print too) have affirm'd the contrary. But alas! the <hi>Truth</hi> is, This <hi>Praediction</hi> came from him by way of <hi>Irony,</hi> I doubt. otherwise I could shew him its just Verification.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="May" type="month">
               <pb facs="tcp:152706:6"/>
               <head>Observations on MAY.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>Says <hi>Truth</hi> it self,— <hi>Believe</hi> and <hi>Saved</hi> be;</l>
                     <l>Yet show some <hi>Signs</hi> of thy <hi>Integrity</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>In <hi>Pious Works;</hi> By which a <hi>Christian's</hi> known,</l>
                     <l>And not by Beastly <hi>Ralling Order</hi> down.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Christ</hi> came not to <hi>Destroy!</hi> but to fulfil</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Will</hi> of <hi>God:</hi> The <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Humane Will.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THe <hi>Libeller</hi> is here upon the <hi>High Rope:</hi> and tells us,— That <hi>Lorain, Ireland, Russia,</hi> and <hi>Poland,</hi> are <hi>violently, threat'ned with the effects of the</hi> Suns <hi>eclipse in</hi> Taurus: <hi>when</hi> Mars <hi>comes to the Square thereof in</hi> June <hi>and</hi> July, But, blessed be God, we have liv'd past those very <hi>months</hi> and do not find <hi>Lorain Restor'd,</hi> nor <hi>Ireland Disturb'd:</hi> which were the <hi>Libellers</hi> groundless <hi>Hopes.</hi> We know who he means by his <hi>Turk of Christendom</hi> in <hi>February;</hi> but let him, as an <hi>Artist,</hi> tell me if ever he knew any <hi>Person</hi> who had the Lord of his <hi>Horoscope in secunda Domo,</hi> that ever parted with any thing easily that he got, be it hy Conquest, or otherwise? And for the Affairs in <hi>Ireland,</hi> they are in a very thriving Posture, and daily like to be better. Let the <hi>Libeller</hi> read Mr. <hi>Whalley</hi>'s Judgement on that <hi>Gallant Countrey,</hi> for 1687. and be convinced— That <hi>eclipses,</hi> Govern'd by <hi>Venus,</hi> are Innocuous both to Places and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, unless aggravated by other Circumstances.— But he concludes,— <hi>Popery will not do.</hi> And, why not, <hi>Libel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler!</hi> If <hi>Red-letter'd-men</hi> are <hi>Loyal,</hi> as lately you allowed them.— But, <hi>'tis not good</hi> (says he) <hi>to promote it by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring Scandalous Favourers of it;</hi> I say so too. But where are any such Prefer'd? If he can find any; let him produce <hi>One</hi> Honest Man of his <hi>Faction</hi> to throw the <hi>Stone.</hi> The <hi>Wretch</hi> is brim full of <hi>envy,</hi> and is much troubled that the KING hath any <hi>Loyal men</hi> fit to Serve Him. But <hi>Popery! Popery!</hi> That's the <hi>Term</hi> with all those who know not what <hi>Religion,</hi> or <hi>Catholick</hi> is.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="June" type="month">
               <pb facs="tcp:152706:6"/>
               <head>Observations on JUNE.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>To <hi>Rail</hi> at <hi>Priests,</hi> and <hi>Ban</hi> the <hi>Holy Cross.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>May purchase to thy <hi>Soul</hi> eternal <hi>Loss.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Alas! No <hi>Inquisition</hi> here can free</l>
                     <l>Us, from the <hi>Abyss</hi> of <hi>Eternity</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To <hi>Rome</hi> none need be <hi>Slaves!</hi> 'Tis <hi>Heresy</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Ingulpths our <hi>Souls!</hi> The <hi>True Church</hi> sets us <hi>Free.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>NOw the <hi>Libeller</hi> doubles his Threats at <hi>London,</hi> bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding us remember the <hi>Sun is in</hi> Gemini, <hi>in Opposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to</hi> Jupiter <hi>in</hi> Sagitary; <hi>and that it affects</hi> London <hi>about Religion, Liberty of Conscience, Persecution,</hi> &amp;c.— Sir, we do remember all you say very well, and affirm, <hi>secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum Artem,</hi> that though <hi>Jupiter</hi> be in <hi>Opposition</hi> of the <hi>Sun,</hi> &amp;c. Yet hath <hi>London</hi> felt no <hi>Persecution</hi> in this Month, either for <hi>Religion,</hi> or ought else; but the plain contrary. We must read the <hi>Libeller backward,</hi> as Men read <hi>Hebrew.</hi> In the room of <hi>Persecution,</hi> we enjoy <hi>Liberty of Conscience</hi> in the Service of God. A <hi>Dispensation!</hi> that we are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted to <hi>Heaven</hi> for, and to a <hi>Gracious King;</hi> who is a true <hi>Nursing Father</hi> to all His People! A <hi>Dispensation!</hi> This <hi>Libeller</hi> no more <hi>Foresaw,</hi> than <hi>Wished.</hi> And, now I would have the <hi>Libeller</hi> remember, That in true <hi>Astrology, No aspects of the Fortunate Stars,</hi> (in a strict sense) <hi>can be hurtful,</hi> much less can they <hi>change</hi> their <hi>essential Virtues</hi> into Malignity, <hi>vide.</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r <hi>C. H.</hi> p. 513. The <hi>Libeller</hi> hath therefore <hi>Forged</hi> this Judgement; <hi>contra artem,</hi> on purpose to Create <hi>Disturbances.</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lly Soul! to imagine that the <hi>Specifical</hi> Virtues of the <hi>Stars</hi> can be changed. They may, indeed, (as <hi>Astrologers,</hi> with good Reason allow) be <hi>Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,</hi> or <hi>Remitted,</hi> but never <hi>alter'd:</hi> and <hi>Magis &amp; minus non tollunt speciem:</hi> Their <hi>essences</hi> must remain the <hi>same</hi> for ever.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="July" type="month">
               <pb facs="tcp:152706:7"/>
               <head>Observations on JULY.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>Nor can our <hi>Holy Mother</hi> give command</l>
                     <l>To <hi>Murder</hi> men! For, on Her <hi>Ivory</hi> Hand</l>
                     <l>A <hi>Spotless White</hi> is seen! <hi>No Blood-Stains</hi> there,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Schismaticks</hi> for <hi>Blood!</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> for <hi>Prayer.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But this vain <hi>Wight</hi> believes that <hi>Christians</hi> can</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Command,</hi> what s <hi>Disallow'd</hi> by th' <hi>Alcoran.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THe <hi>Libeller</hi> tells us, <hi>Mars Retrograde, in Opposition to the place of the last Conjunction</hi> 1682. <hi>shews loss to the</hi> Turk <hi>by the arms of his enemies.</hi> But, what hath the <hi>Turk</hi> to do with <hi>Aquary</hi> and <hi>Leo?</hi> the place and opposite of that <hi>Conjunction.</hi> I wonder he had not levell'd this Arrow against the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Popery,</hi> (the only <hi>Butt</hi> or <hi>Mark</hi> of his <hi>malice!</hi>) but he had not the <hi>luck</hi> to hit on't. In truth it is of no great moment to either, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat the <hi>Libeller</hi> loves to hang <hi>great Weights</hi> on <hi>little Wyers.</hi> For <hi>Mars</hi> comes every year to the <hi>place,</hi> and <hi>Opposition</hi> of that <hi>Conjunction,</hi> and should, by his Argument, as often put the <hi>Turk</hi> into a <hi>Feaver.</hi> But alas! <hi>Transits</hi> are but of little effect when other <hi>Influences</hi> are absent. There are other more preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <hi>Causes</hi> that <hi>menace</hi> the <hi>Turks,</hi> of which I perceive <hi>He</hi>'s ignorant; and I have not room here to inform him.— But the <hi>Libeller</hi> talks of a <hi>New Plot, and Accusations for Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, upon the Opposition of</hi> Mars <hi>and</hi> Mercury; <hi>and</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>and</hi> France <hi>are concern'd,</hi> The Man is willing to put his <hi>fellow associates</hi> in good Heart, that when he hath set us together by the <hi>Ears,</hi> they may take a <hi>trip</hi> over, to help on the <hi>Rebellion.</hi> Ungrateful <hi>Brute!</hi> Thus, without <hi>Reason,</hi> to <hi>Rave</hi> against his <hi>Native Countrey,</hi> He was affraid, to take notice of the formidable <hi>Trine of the Sun and Jupiter,</hi> which, with respect to a commanding <hi>Radical constitution,</hi> and other concurring Circumstances, bodes <hi>England</hi> much good in Earnest, and Anticipates his <hi>Plots, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons,</hi> &amp;c. But this was not for the <hi>Libellers tooth</hi> to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="August" type="month">
               <pb facs="tcp:152706:7"/>
               <head>Observations on AUGUST.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>Let <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> and all the <hi>World</hi> make known,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>prejudice</hi> that <hi>Priests;</hi> as <hi>Priests,</hi> have done.</l>
                     <l>And then <hi>consider</hi> how this <hi>Wretched Man,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>At th' <hi>Sacred</hi> Name of <hi>Priest,</hi> dare <hi>Curse</hi> and <hi>Ban,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But <hi>They</hi> that Freedom take <hi>Gods Priests</hi> to <hi>Curse,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Would serve <hi>Kings</hi> so! and (had they <hi>Power) worse.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>OUr Canting <hi>Libeller</hi> here tells us,— <hi>That from the Opposition of the</hi> Sun <hi>and</hi> Mars <hi>last</hi> Lunation, <hi>there will be more Murders, Duels, and Violence of all sorts.</hi> Where by the way, I must tell him, he's guilty of another <hi>Cretism,</hi> and false Art together. For that Opposition was not <hi>Angular,</hi> but <hi>Cadent:</hi> Celebrated in the <hi>Twelfth</hi> and <hi>Sixth</hi> Houses: And therefore could not intimate <hi>publick Murders,</hi> or <hi>Violence,</hi> &amp;c. But rather <hi>Fears, Anxieties, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisonments, Sorrows, Bodily Infirmities,</hi> and the like. This he knows to be the true <hi>English</hi> of that <hi>Opposition,</hi> and not what he suggests. But he goes on,— Italy <hi>is under some apprehension of Troubles;</hi> some of the <hi>Sacred Crew</hi> at <hi>Rome disagree about power, precedence,</hi> &amp;c, Here the <hi>Libeller</hi> hath <hi>transfer'd</hi> a term of <hi>Art</hi> used among <hi>Saylers, (viz.</hi> the <hi>Boat-Swain</hi> and his <hi>Crew,</hi>) to the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals▪</hi> as having just the same (but no more) Reverence for <hi>Them.</hi>— Well! <hi>but nothing</hi> comes of <hi>it but words and talk.</hi> Nay, I dare lay a Wager with him, nor that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For <hi>Jupiter</hi> (the Patron of the <hi>Sacred Crew,</hi> as he scurrilously terms them,) is in <hi>Sagitary,</hi> comforting the <hi>Horoscope</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> by a Noble <hi>Trigonal</hi> Beam: And <hi>Trines</hi> never <hi>disturb,</hi> but <hi>assist</hi> such <hi>places</hi> and <hi>persons</hi> that <hi>share</hi> in the <hi>Influence.</hi> But the <hi>Libellers</hi> Praedictions never afford any <hi>Musick,</hi> unless the <hi>Priest</hi> bear a part, like the <hi>Dumb Jack</hi> in the <hi>Virginals.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="September" type="month">
               <pb facs="tcp:152706:8"/>
               <head>Observations on SEPTEMBER.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>The <hi>Voice</hi> of th' <hi>People</hi> cannot always be</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Voice</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> W'have seen the <hi>Contrary.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Frauds,</hi> and <hi>False Rumours</hi> have their <hi>Root</hi> in <hi>Hell.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And 'twas for <hi>London</hi>'s <hi>Sins,</hi> that <hi>London</hi> Fell.</l>
                     <l>But that <hi>Rome Burnt it,</hi> Swear't who will! I Fear</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Martyr's Blood!</hi> made <hi>London</hi> pay so <hi>Dear.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>NOw the <hi>Libeller</hi> talks of <hi>Peace and Reconciliation▪ but that the Troubl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s of</hi> Europe <hi>will not over, while the Power of the</hi> Conjunction <hi>of</hi> Saturn <hi>and</hi> Jupiter <hi>lasts.— And that</hi> Mars <hi>in</hi> Aquary <hi>will irritate the Effects thereof.</hi> This is somewhat of the <hi>Cuckows</hi> Note he Sung before, and for which I have already reckon'd with him. But yet I ask h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, whether that <hi>Conjuncton</hi> be not more for <hi>quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> than <hi>creating Troubles,</hi> since <hi>Jupiter</hi> is the <hi>Ruling Planet</hi> therein? Some trouble, 'tis true, there may be to bring <hi>Beggars to the Stocks,</hi> and then to get in their Legs. But <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Unity</hi> will be the <hi>Consequence</hi> of that <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction.</hi> And I can tell him, that after the Celebration of that <hi>Conjunction,</hi> his Patrons, <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> and <hi>Monmouth,</hi> &amp;c. never <hi>prosper'd.</hi> He proceeds,— <hi>The present Wars shall Travel from one Countrey to another, till all</hi> Europe <hi>have tasted thereof.</hi> But, (as I said) the <hi>Ruling Planet</hi> in that <hi>Conjunction,</hi> is for <hi>Peace,</hi> and for freeing us from <hi>Disquiet,</hi> not fomenting it.— But lo! He changes his Scene, to <hi>Whispers an</hi> England <hi>about a Man of Quality, Old, and Infirm.</hi> Who he is, we'll tell you when the <hi>Libeller</hi> hath told us. Sure he means not Sir <hi>P. W.</hi> who plays at <hi>Hide</hi> and <hi>Seek,</hi> to avoid the Punishment due to <hi>Perjury.</hi> He's an <hi>Old Man;</hi> and was of <hi>Quality</hi> too, when he (as this <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beller</hi>) affirm'd the <hi>Papists Burnt</hi> London, <hi>and</hi> maliciously Order'd it (when <hi>Mayor</hi>) to be Inscribed on the <hi>Monument</hi> at <hi>London-Bridge.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="October" type="month">
               <pb facs="tcp:152706:8"/>
               <head>Observations on OCTOBER.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>The <hi>Libeller</hi> Rails still: and let them <hi>Rail;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Try how his <hi>Brutish Morals</hi> will prevail</l>
                     <l>For his <hi>Despised Cause.</hi>— For <hi>Godfrey's Blood,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Oh! that the <hi>Truth</hi> were fully understood!</l>
                     <l>But <hi>Prance!</hi> unhappy <hi>Prance!</hi> hath so much done,</l>
                     <l>As (not to <hi>clear</hi> it, yet) to <hi>Quit</hi> just <hi>Rome.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THe <hi>Libeller</hi> tells us—<hi>The New Moon in conjunction of</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, <hi>and Square of</hi> Jupiter, <hi>concerns</hi> Germany, England, ('twere much if <hi>England</hi> should be out.) <hi>Denmark,</hi> &amp;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>about such Men and things as relate to Wars,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>because</hi> Mars <hi>in</hi> Aquary <hi>is in Trine of them all.</hi>—What? in <hi>Trine</hi> of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi> too? you must lay your <hi>lies</hi> closer together, you'l be discover'd else. But he proceeds,—<hi>The effect will be T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, —Practiced for Villanies sake</hi> (as all Treachery is, sure.) <hi>It concerns the Kings of</hi> Denmark <hi>and</hi> Portugal, <hi>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Duke of</hi> Brandenburg. And so it may, and yet never hurt them, unless <hi>Trines</hi> can be turn'd into <hi>Aspects</hi> of <hi>enmity.</hi> —Soon after he tells us,—<hi>Of a noise about Peace and Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation, and that the Aspests of the Month incline to quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness.</hi> Like the <hi>Traveller</hi> in the <hi>Fable,</hi> that could blow <hi>Hot</hi> and <hi>Cold</hi> in a <hi>Breath,</hi> &amp;c. He hath Created <hi>War</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> from the same <hi>Causes.</hi> For which his <hi>Delphian</hi> Cunning, let the <hi>Satyr</hi> be his <hi>Censurer.</hi>—He Concludes,—<hi>Some Reverend Right-Lin'd Clergy-man receives considerable referment.</hi> He distinguishes of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> as <hi>Mathematicians</hi> of their <hi>Triangles;</hi> makes some <hi>Right-Lin'd,</hi> some <hi>Spherical,</hi> &amp;c. —But now, suppose his <hi>Right-Lin'd Clergy-man</hi> should prove <hi>Spherical;</hi> Or, what if no such matter happen at all, as 'tis most likely; (for <hi>Jupiter</hi> makes no perfect Aspect with any <hi>Planet</hi> in the whole Month, <hi>praeter Lunam.</hi>) Why then the trifling <hi>Libeller</hi> hath lost his <hi>Jest.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="November" type="month">
               <pb facs="tcp:152706:9"/>
               <head>Observations on NOVEMBER.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e, <hi>Blasphemy</hi> and <hi>Treason</hi> arm his <hi>Pen,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ike at <hi>God,</hi> as well as scratch at <hi>Men.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Behold an <hi>Atheists Impudence!</hi> so great,</l>
                     <l>He Counts both <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Priesthood</hi> too, a <hi>Cheat.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Take heed Curs'd <hi>Corah!</hi> least thy Mother Earth</l>
                     <l>Do <hi>swallow</hi> thee, as an <hi>untimely Birth.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>WE have often been told of <hi>Popish Massacres, Bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ck B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lls, Spanish Pilgrimes,</hi> &amp;c. as if all the <hi>wicked Plots</hi> in the World were to be found among <hi>atholicks;</hi> and that the <hi>Protestant associating Party,</hi> were the <hi>Sheep</hi> and <hi>Doves</hi> of Nature, the very <hi>Pictures</hi> of true <hi>Innocence!</hi> But the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beller</hi> here proves to us, that those pacifick <hi>Umble Bees</hi> have <hi>stings,</hi> and can shew them too for a need. For thus the <hi>Bloody miscreant</hi> Writes,—
<q>
                     <l>Never be <hi>bubbled</hi> by a <hi>Popish Lie,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Rather then that, <hi>Resolve, Revenge,</hi> and <hi>Die.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And in his Epistle to Protestants.</p>
               <q>Give not your <hi>Faith</hi> up, nor yet <hi>Tamely</hi> Die.</q>
               <p>He hath elsewhere declaim'd against <hi>Passive Obedience,</hi> and here excites to <hi>Resolution, Revenge,</hi> and not to <hi>Die tamely!</hi> what <hi>Rombald, Ferguson,</hi> or impudent Incendiary of them all, could have vented more <hi>Treason</hi> in so little <hi>Room,</hi> to have animated a <hi>Rebellion.—Resolve!</hi> you have been good at this before, as appears by the Testimonies, in the History of the <hi>Rye-House</hi> Conspiracy against you; which your <hi>Flight</hi> and present <hi>Malice</hi> prove to be true.—<hi>Revenge!</hi> on whom? who hath done you wrong? not <hi>tamely Die!</hi> how comes your <hi>Life</hi> in Question, unless you have forfeited it by your <hi>Treasons?</hi> —Give not your <hi>Faith</hi> up! —What <hi>Faith</hi> hath an <hi>Atheist</hi> to loose? —<hi>Sir,</hi> your <hi>Conscience</hi> haunts you, and ever will, for your <hi>Treasonous</hi> and <hi>wicked contrivances</hi> against your <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Country.</hi> 'Tis in that <hi>Glass</hi> you behold your <hi>wicked Actions,</hi> and thence proceeds your <hi>Distracted Fears.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There's little else in <hi>November</hi> worth minding; save that the <hi>Libeller</hi> makes the Planet <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs</hi> a <hi>Don-Quixet,</hi> and sets him a <hi>Fighting</hi> by himself.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="December" type="month">
               <pb facs="tcp:152706:9"/>
               <head>Observations on DECEMBER.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>The <hi>Canting Varlet</hi> thinks he hath done well;</l>
                     <l>To <hi>Grin</hi> at <hi>God,</hi> and 'gainst his <hi>King</hi> Rebell:</l>
                     <l>And, for to <hi>Menace</hi> Gods true <hi>Church</hi> again,</l>
                     <l>Raises his <hi>Raptures</hi> to a higher strain:</l>
                     <l>And boldly <hi>boasts</hi> her certain <hi>down-fall</hi> here;</l>
                     <l>When nothing like the <hi>Contrary's</hi> more <hi>clear.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>FRom the last <hi>New Moon</hi> being in <hi>Sagitary,</hi> in <hi>Square</hi> of <hi>Mars</hi> in <hi>Pisces,</hi> and in <hi>Conjunction</hi> of <hi>Mars</hi> at the <hi>First Quarter.</hi> The <hi>Libeller</hi> Predicts—<hi>Persecution for Religion, or some New Invention to punish people for difference in opinion from those in Power; but whether it extend to life or lesser pain, he cannot determine.</hi> And therein he's wary.—But Sir! your <hi>Art</hi> teaches you that Persecution proceeds not from particular <hi>Lunations,</hi> but <hi>General Constitutions.</hi> Consult your <hi>skill</hi> again, and tell me, are not the two <hi>Superiours</hi> in <hi>Cardinal Signes?</hi> and is not <hi>Saturn</hi> in friendly Aspect to the late <hi>triple Conjunction</hi> of <hi>him,</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> in <hi>Leo?</hi>—I affirm, that in stead of the <hi>Persecution,</hi> this Libeller threatens us with, that the <hi>Actions</hi> of this <hi>Month,</hi> and the last also, with some Months succeeding, will make for the <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>ease</hi> of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and the <hi>Pious,</hi> (yet Warlike) Ruler thereof. And this the <hi>Libeller</hi> might have known, had he consider'd <hi>Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions</hi> and <hi>Profections,</hi> and compared them with the great <hi>triple ruling Conjunction.</hi> But I will not charge the <hi>Libeller</hi> as guilty of the knowledge of so much <hi>Astrology,</hi> as goes to the understanding of <hi>Cardan's—Multiplicatio effectus Siderum Secreta.</hi>—He says, <hi>The square of the Sun and Mars incline to down-right Murther,</hi> &amp;c. But this must needs prove <hi>false;</hi> The Planets squaring being govern'd by <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them in <hi>Interficient</hi> Decades, or Terms.</p>
               <p>Thus have I done with the <hi>Libellers monthly Predictions</hi> and <hi>Poetry,</hi> (or <hi>Ravings</hi> rather,) full Fraught with <hi>Falshood, Treason,</hi> and <hi>Blasphemy;</hi> and of so <hi>black</hi> a <hi>Die,</hi> that all the Water between <hi>Us</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> will never be able to <hi>wash</hi> away.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="examination">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:152706:10"/>
            <head>THE <hi>LIBELLERS</hi> Lying Chronology EXAMINED.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Since <hi>Phocas Murther'd</hi> his <hi>Master,</hi> and his <hi>Children,</hi> got the <hi>Empire,</hi> and then <hi>Piously</hi> set up the <hi>Pope. 1085.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS if there had never been a <hi>Pope</hi> until the time of <hi>Phocas.</hi> An egregious, yet pleasant falshood! The Man sure never saw <hi>Platina,</hi> or <hi>Heylin.</hi> —But here the story of <hi>Phocas</hi> out of <hi>Fox.</hi> —<q>This <hi>Phocas</hi> comming up to be <hi>Emperour,</hi>—Thinking to establish his Empire with friendship and favour of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and especially with <hi>Boniface</hi> the Third, the <hi>Bishop of Rome,</hi> quickly condescended to all his <hi>Petitions,</hi> and so granted him, (as it is said (mark it!) to be, that he would) the <hi>Universal</hi> and <hi>Head Bishop</hi> over all <hi>Christian Churches.</hi>
                  </q> So that you see <hi>Phocas</hi> did not <hi>make</hi> Boniface <hi>Pope,</hi> but <hi>found</hi> him so. Only, for quieting of differences between the <hi>two</hi> (then) contending <hi>Interests,</hi> he justly preserv'd the <hi>Title</hi> of <hi>Universal Bishop</hi> to the <hi>See</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> We wish that had been the worst act of which <hi>Phocas</hi> had been guilty. He was, 'tis true, a <hi>wicked Man,</hi> and came to a <hi>suitable</hi> end. God is ever just.—But <hi>Fox,</hi> (so by Nature, as well as Name) as knowing the <hi>falshood</hi> of his <hi>Relation,</hi> claps in the <hi>Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thesis,</hi> (as it is said) to <hi>escape</hi> by, in case of pursuit. For he knew well enough that the <hi>Bishop</hi> of <hi>Constantinople</hi> did never dispute the <hi>Title</hi> of <hi>Universal Bishop,</hi> with the <hi>Bishop of Rome.</hi> Neither did that <hi>Title</hi> begin (by <hi>Phocas</hi>) to be attributed to the <hi>Pope,</hi> but from the time of the Emperour <hi>Marcian;</hi> above an 150 years before <hi>Phocas,</hi> it had been <hi>exhibited</hi> to <hi>Him</hi> in the Council of <hi>Chalcedon.</hi> And, after that, under the Emperour <hi>Justinian:</hi> above 50 years before the time of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152706:10"/>
                  <hi>Phocas,</hi> it had been given him in <hi>Constantinople</hi> it self. So that <hi>Phocas</hi> was as far from <hi>Piously</hi> setting up the <hi>Pope,</hi> as this <hi>Libeller</hi> is from setting out the <hi>Truth.—Vide Fox, Vol.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 155. and <hi>Card. Perron's</hi> Reply to <hi>K. James</hi> I, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>Popish Powder Treason Nov.</hi> 5. at which time all the <hi>Protestant Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry</hi> were to be <hi>murder'd</hi> in the <hi>Parliament House.</hi> 82.</head>
               <p>IF this were really a <hi>Plot</hi> of the <hi>Papists</hi> hatching, (we do not deny but there were some deluded <hi>Catholicks</hi> in it▪ and <hi>suffer'd</hi> for it,) it was the most <hi>ridiculous</hi> (next to <hi>Oates</hi>'s Plot) that ever was heard of. For there was no manner of <hi>Provision</hi> made for <hi>Security</hi> of their own <hi>Friends.</hi> Besides, it was a <hi>Catholick Lord, (viz.</hi> the Lord <hi>Mount-Eagle</hi>) that <hi>discover'd</hi> it by a <hi>Letter</hi> sent to him. A great sign that all the Eminent <hi>Catholicks</hi> were not concern'd (except <hi>passively</hi>) in that <hi>horrid Contrivance.</hi> And had the <hi>design</hi> taken the pretended effect, the <hi>Popish Powder</hi> (as the <hi>Libeller</hi> idly terms it) could never have distinguish'd between <hi>Catholicks</hi> and <hi>Protestants:</hi> So that the <hi>Popish Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry,</hi> must have been <hi>murther'd</hi> also. But be it as it will, I will, sing in <hi>Cons<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rt</hi> with the late Loyal Sir <hi>George Wharton.</hi>—
<q>
                     <l>Twit <hi>Rome</hi> no longer with the <hi>Powder-Plot,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The <hi>Doctrine</hi> is half <hi>English,</hi> and half <hi>Scot.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>City of</hi> London was <hi>Burnt,</hi> by <hi>whom</hi> 'tis well known. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>21.</head>
               <p>I wish it were! The <hi>dreadful,</hi> and never to be forgotten <hi>Fire</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> began <hi>September</hi> the 2, 1666. Many noises and rumours were spread concerning the <hi>cause</hi> thereof. Some, affirming the <hi>Papists</hi> did it. Others, the <hi>Fanaticks.</hi> Others, not sticking to say, it was the <hi>King</hi> himself. Whether will not <hi>malice</hi> read the <hi>Rascality?</hi>— If the <hi>Papists</hi> did it, they were the most <hi>imprudent men</hi> in the World; since as well their <hi>Protection,</hi> as <hi>Riches,</hi> and <hi>Relations,</hi> being in <hi>London,</hi> they must in such an <hi>Action</hi> labour'd the <hi>Rnine</hi> of themselves. If it were done by any <hi>Power</hi> then that of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:152706:11"/> I have great reason to believe, that, not the <hi>Papists,</hi> but <hi>Phanaticks</hi> were the instruments. For in a <hi>Gazet</hi> of <hi>April</hi> 1666. I read, <hi>That some of the Republican Party,</hi> (as confessed by some of them, then <hi>dying</hi> for <hi>Treason.) by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sulting</hi> Lilly's <hi>Almanack of that year, found</hi> September <hi>to be a month fit for their destructive and Rebellions purposes against the King and Government.</hi>—Albeit, it seems clear to me (if I may not offend in saying so,) that had not the hand of <hi>Heaven</hi> most manifestly appear'd therein, so <hi>vast</hi> and <hi>prodigious</hi> a <hi>Fire,</hi> could never have happ'ned in so <hi>short a time.</hi> I make no doubt but the good, (or rather bad) <hi>wishes,</hi> and perhaps, the <hi>Actions</hi> too, of some <hi>enemies</hi> to <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Kingdom</hi> might not be wanting. But that <hi>Heaven</hi> had a great hand in it, is very plain, to all reasonable and considering Men. Seeing this <hi>dismal Accident</hi> was preceded by a more then ordinary <hi>dry Summer,</hi> preparing the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of that Glorious <hi>City,</hi> fit for the consuming <hi>Flames;</hi> And at the very time of its commencement, and all the time of its continuance also, a mighty <hi>East-Wind</hi> prevail'd. So that neither the stately Structures of <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>Halls,</hi> and other Sumptuous and Noble <hi>Edifices,</hi> were able to give a check, or opposition thereunto. But lo! at last, when as we may justly conceive its <hi>Commission</hi> for <hi>Destruction,</hi> began to <hi>expire,</hi> the <hi>Wind</hi> changed, and the <hi>Fire</hi> ceas'd to <hi>rage,</hi> and stop'd even at <hi>Paper Buildings,</hi> as it were, or Houses (otherwise) unable to oppose so mighty a <hi>Devourer.</hi> I am morally assured, that, had there not been <hi>digitus Dei</hi> in it, should <hi>Ten</hi> several Persons with Authority, have gone to <hi>Ten</hi> several equi-distant <hi>Places</hi> of that great <hi>City,</hi> on purpose to <hi>destroy</hi> it; They could never (without the assistance of such a <hi>Wind</hi> and <hi>Drought</hi>) have ruin'd so many stately <hi>Edifices,</hi> and so many <hi>Thousand Houses</hi> in so short a time.</p>
               <p>Besides, this dreadful Fire was long since Prophecy'd of by <hi>Michael Nostradamus,</hi> and (to shew that all <hi>Proph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cies</hi> are not to be slighted) the very <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Propinquate cause</hi> thereof was expressed by him, as you may find, <hi>Cent.</hi> 2, <hi>Stanz.</hi> 51.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Le Sang du juste a Londres fera faut,</l>
                  <l>Bruslez par feu, de vingt &amp; trois les six, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:152706:11"/>
               <p>Which may admit of this <hi>English.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For</hi> Blood <hi>of th'</hi> just <hi>fair</hi> London, Fire <hi>shall</hi> vex,</l>
                  <l>Which happen <hi>will,</hi> in the year <hi>Sixty Six,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               </q>
               <p>By the <hi>Blood</hi> of the <hi>Just,</hi> must be meant the <hi>Blood</hi> of that Blessed Martyr <hi>King</hi> CHARLES the I. who was barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously <hi>murther'd</hi> at his own Door, <hi>January</hi> 30, 1648 —Nay, to add t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this, I can truly affirm, That amazing <hi>Accident</hi> was <hi>Predicted</hi> in two <hi>Almanacks,</hi> wrote near a Twelve-Month before it happen'd; <hi>viz Trigg,</hi> and <hi>another;</hi> in which later; the <hi>Prediction</hi> was expung'd by the <hi>Licenser.</hi> But let any stupendious Accident whatsoever befall us, whether from <hi>Heaven,</hi> or by <hi>men,</hi> the <hi>Libeller</hi> is certain to Father all on the <hi>Papists.</hi> And, be sure also, that he means the <hi>English Papists,</hi> the natural Subjects of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>Hubert,</hi> (that died for the <hi>Fact</hi>) was a <hi>Foreigner,</hi> and a <hi>French-man.</hi> And 'tis easie to remember, that <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France</hi> were then in <hi>Hostility,</hi> they joyning the <hi>Hollander</hi> against us. Now, what an <hi>enemy</hi> doth, (in case <hi>Hubert</hi> did it, which the <hi>Observator</hi> proves not possible, by sundry <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrative Reasons.</hi>) is not to be imputed to <hi>Religion,</hi> but to the <hi>fewd</hi> and <hi>distance</hi> between the <hi>parties</hi> concern'd.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>Popish Massacre in Ireland,</hi> where 300000 <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants</hi> were <hi>murder'd,</hi> and this done by <hi>Authority.</hi> 46.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Libeller</hi> had done well, if he had nam'd the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</hi> If any Authority Commanded so <hi>Barbarous</hi> an Act, it must be either <hi>lawful,</hi> or <hi>un-lawful.</hi> If the <hi>later,</hi> all <hi>good men</hi> will <hi>bewail</hi> the <hi>misfortune,</hi> as much as the <hi>Libeller.</hi> For then it is <hi>Vis,</hi> not <hi>Jus.</hi> And <hi>Force</hi> and <hi>Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence</hi> may <hi>effect</hi> what <hi>Law</hi> or <hi>Reason</hi> will not <hi>justifie.</hi> But if the <hi>Former,</hi> I would fain know of the <hi>Libeller</hi> (when he hath consulted his <hi>Casuists</hi>) how Men acting under a <hi>lawful</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and not going beyond their <hi>Commission,</hi> can be guilty of <hi>murther?</hi> And if they exceed their <hi>Commission,</hi> they cease to be <hi>Sons</hi> of a <hi>lawful Authority,</hi> and adopt themselves <hi>Heirs</hi> of <hi>violence.</hi> Moreover, I require of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152706:12"/> him to poduce <hi>one Commission</hi> from any <hi>Lawful Authority</hi> for the Proof of what he boldly thus asserts: wherein I doubt, he'll be as much to seek, as his Friend <hi>Titus</hi> was, to procure <hi>one</hi> of <hi>Paulus de Oliva</hi>'s <hi>Commissions</hi> for the support of his <hi>Damnable</hi> PLOT. This piece of <hi>Chronology</hi> must pass therefore for a <hi>Horrid Scandal</hi> upon all the Loyal Party in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and likewise upon the Sacred memory of that Pious Prince and Martyr, King <hi>Charles</hi> I. Moreover, I have read many of the Pamphlets of those times, and all the Printed Papers that passed between the two Illustrious and thrice Noble Lords, <hi>viz.</hi> the Duke of <hi>Ormond</hi> his Grace, and the late Earl of <hi>Anglesey,</hi> as also the <hi>Memoires</hi> of the late Right Honourable Earl of <hi>Castlehaven,</hi> relating to the Troubles of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and find nothing in any of them to countenance what the <hi>Libeller</hi> maliciously suggests. This therefore I brand for a <hi>Horrid Falshood;</hi> though I remember the <hi>Mobilee</hi> were then strangely frighted with <hi>Monstrous Pictures,</hi> as if all the <hi>Ten Persecutions</hi> were there, and only there extant.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Sir <hi>Edumndbury Godfrey</hi> was murder'd at <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merset-House. 9</hi>
               </head>
               <p>GOd forbid that this should be true, though <hi>Bedloe</hi> and others have <hi>Sworn</hi> it! The <hi>Libeller</hi> Prints this with as assured a Confidence, as if he had been <hi>One</hi> of the <hi>murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers;</hi> or, a <hi>Sharer</hi> in the 2000 <hi>l.</hi> which <hi>Bedloe</hi> has Sworn to be offer'd for carrying away the <hi>Dead Body</hi> Monstrous Villain! that dares be so <hi>positive</hi> in a matter so <hi>Obscure!</hi> the non knowledge whereof is as much the Amazement of the World, as the non-discovery of the <hi>Vizzarded Villains</hi> who were on the <hi>Scaffold, January</hi> the 30th. 1648. when King <hi>Charles</hi> I. was <hi>murder'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was an unhappiness in a <hi>greater,</hi> and much more Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Person</hi> than the <hi>Libeller, viz.</hi> He that <hi>Preach'd</hi> this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate Gentleman's <hi>Funeral Sermon,</hi> (Oh! the <hi>Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft</hi> of <hi>Credulity</hi>) as to lay the <hi>murder</hi> on the <hi>Papists;</hi> and this too, before any <hi>Evidence</hi> appear'd to justifie the <hi>Fact.</hi> The <hi>Sermon</hi> was Preach'd <hi>October</hi> the 31st. 1678. But
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152706:12"/>
                  <hi>William Bedloe</hi> did not <hi>accuse</hi> himself publickly of that <hi>Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid murder,</hi> untill <hi>November</hi> the 7. following. And 'tis well known, that <hi>Miles Prance</hi> came not in until <hi>December</hi> the 22. following.— As for <hi>Bedloe,</hi> I leave him to be dealt with by the <hi>Righteous Judge</hi> of Heaven and Earth Yet, may we reasonably be convinc'd, That <hi>Pardon, Pension,</hi> and <hi>Money</hi> in Hand, are very great <hi>Temptations</hi> to Men of no Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and needy too. But for <hi>Prance,</hi> he hath own'd his <hi>Perjury,</hi> and been <hi>punished</hi> for it. And I wish that others concern'd in that Barbarous <hi>murder,</hi> would discover the <hi>Truth</hi> thereof, for their <hi>Souls Health,</hi> and <hi>Satisfaction</hi> of the <hi>Deluded</hi> World; and implore the <hi>pardon</hi> of <hi>Heaven,</hi> and that of His Gracious <hi>Majesty,</hi> for their concealment of so horrid a <hi>Crime</hi> so long, to the provoking of <hi>Gods Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and pulling them down upon us. But though my <hi>Gentleman</hi> be so <hi>positive</hi> as to name the place, where, this <hi>Villanous murder</hi> was committed, yet could I never meet with any who would believe that a <hi>Justice of Peace</hi> should be <hi>Decoy'd</hi> down thither to part a couple of <hi>Rude Fellows,</hi> that were <hi>Fighting</hi> (forsooth!) at Nine a Clock at Night. If they had been <hi>Fighting</hi> in the <hi>Justices Hall,</hi> 'tis true, his <hi>Authority</hi> might have allay'd the <hi>Fray:</hi> but abroad, what could he do? How should he be acknowledg'd? Meer <hi>Stories.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>That Pious Prince, <hi>Charles II.</hi> died a <hi>Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick,</hi> and yet <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England. 2.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ANd yet <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England!</hi> Yes, <hi>Libeller▪</hi> this good <hi>King</hi> did <hi>Die</hi> a <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> and yet <hi>Head</hi> of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Why not? What have you to do with <hi>Liberty of Conscience,</hi> if you will not allow it your <hi>Prince?</hi> What Infamy is it to <hi>Die</hi> a <hi>Roman Catholick?</hi> The <hi>Libeller</hi> and the <hi>Heard,</hi> think their case <hi>Desperate:</hi> But what Learned man ever said so? Do they not rather say, even <hi>They</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that <hi>They</hi> come nearer <hi>Primitive Christianity</hi> than the <hi>Dessenters?</hi> He <hi>Died</hi> a <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholick!</hi> He knew what was best to do. But He <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest</hi> it not all His <hi>life.</hi> Wretched <hi>Traytors!</hi> who Plotted
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152706:13"/> against His <hi>precious life,</hi> even while he was not declar'd to the contrary. You know whereabout I am; the <hi>Rye-House Conspiracy,</hi> you <hi>Varlet!</hi> You were <hi>One</hi> that <hi>Flatter'd</hi> up and down in that <hi>Black Design.</hi> In the mean while the Church of <hi>England</hi> is beholding to you very much, who <hi>Grind</hi> your <hi>Teeth</hi> at the mention of It, as at your <hi>Sovereign.</hi> A <hi>Viper</hi> that hisses at all that are better than it self. Our present Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Monarch</hi> lives a <hi>Catholick,</hi> (and long so <hi>God</hi> grant Him to <hi>live!</hi>) and yet <hi>Head</hi> of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> His Headship over the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is no more a <hi>Bar</hi> to His <hi>living,</hi> or <hi>dying</hi> a Member of the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> (A <hi>Church,</hi> that built all the Famous <hi>Churches</hi> in <hi>England!</hi>) than His <hi>Supremacy</hi> over the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> and <hi>Congregatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Assemblies,</hi> &amp;c. All the People of <hi>England</hi> being <hi>Equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> His <hi>Subjects,</hi> even as to their Religious Worship▪ (if out of the Pale of the <hi>Universal Church,</hi>) and for the <hi>practice</hi> thereof, are accountable to Him as their <hi>Sovereign.</hi> But least this <hi>Libeller</hi> should not truly understand what the Church of <hi>England</hi> is! I refer him to a very Rational Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course lately Published, Entituled, GOOD ADVICE, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>JAMES II.</hi> took His <hi>Coronation Oath,</hi> and was Crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>King</hi> at <hi>Westminster. 2.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is very true, that this most Excellent and greatly <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering Prince,</hi> as He was the <hi>lawful Heir,</hi> is now (by Gods wonderful Providence, Maugre the Malice of all <hi>Exclusio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners) Monarch</hi> of <hi>Great Britain, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c. and as such, was Crowned at <hi>Westminster,</hi> on <hi>April</hi> the 23. 1685. And then, and there did take an <hi>Oath,</hi> called the <hi>Coronation Oath,</hi> as the <hi>Libeller</hi> intimates. What then? was it not of His own <hi>Free Choice?</hi> He was <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England</hi> without it. And, tho' it hath been <hi>Customary</hi> for the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> (I think since the time of King <hi>Richard</hi> I.) to take an <hi>Oath</hi> at their <hi>Coronation,</hi> it is not of irresistable <hi>Obligation,</hi> but <hi>prudence</hi> and <hi>Humanity</hi> that they do so. As Sir <hi>R. Filmore</hi> hath fully proved. <hi>Kings</hi> have their <hi>Patents</hi> from <hi>Heaven,</hi> not <hi>Men.</hi> They are Founded in the Law of <hi>Nature</hi> upon <hi>Paternal Right.</hi> The <hi>Coronation</hi> makes not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152706:13"/> the <hi>King,</hi> but only declares the <hi>Sovereign.</hi> 'Tis <hi>Treason</hi> to Act against the <hi>King,</hi> even before He is <hi>Crown'd</hi> But this Sawcy <hi>Rebel</hi> intimates a <hi>Violation</hi> of that <hi>Oath.</hi> Wherein? In wishing <hi>Well</hi> to what he thinks <hi>Right,</hi> and to which that very <hi>Oath</hi> obliges? In maintaining the Church of <hi>England, statu quo?</hi> In his <hi>Dispensation</hi> for <hi>Liberty of Conscience?</hi> Let the People be Judge who enjoy the benefit of that <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence;</hi> when that your self may come and hold forth, if you were not <hi>Obnoxious</hi> on other <hi>Accounts.</hi> In the mean while, now you talk of <hi>Oaths,</hi> and their <hi>Violation,</hi> but who regards the <hi>Oath</hi> that concerns them? the <hi>Oath</hi> of their <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance?</hi> This <hi>Libeller</hi>'s <hi>Fled</hi> to <hi>Holland</hi> for his <hi>Allegiance;</hi> Will you believe it?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Judge STREET.</hi> and—00000000000— <hi>Tresilian,</hi> &amp;c, 1.</head>
               <p>HEre the <hi>Libeller</hi> accosts us with a <hi>Riddle</hi> under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of a piece of <hi>Chronology.</hi> But we want not an <hi>Oedipus</hi> to unfold it. He seems by this <hi>Aenigma</hi> to menace <hi>Eleven</hi> of the <hi>Twelve</hi> Reverend <hi>Judges</hi> of the Nation. But <hi>One</hi> of them he hath mercy for; (impudent Varlet!) that I believe will scarce give him <hi>Thanks</hi> for his <hi>Civility.</hi> Howbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it, the other <hi>Eleven,</hi> understood by his <hi>Eleven Cyphers,</hi> must be <hi>Tresilianiz'd,</hi> (i. e.) in plain <hi>English, Hang'd.</hi> [The <hi>Libeller</hi> knows whose <hi>Destiny</hi> that is, if his <hi>Nativity</hi> belie him not.] How dares this <hi>Fellow</hi> thus presume to <hi>sit</hi> in <hi>Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> upon the Learned and Loyal <hi>Judges!</hi> What have those Reverend <hi>Sages</hi> done, as deserves thus to be <hi>Libel'd?</hi> They all most happily draw in a <hi>Yoak</hi> together for the good of the King and Kingdom. That <hi>One Worthy Person</hi> he men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as well as the <hi>other Eleven.</hi> There are no <hi>Dissenters</hi> among Them. 'Tis therefore a notorious boldness in the <hi>Libeller</hi> thus to <hi>Divide</hi> Them. As if <hi>Eleven</hi> of Them had agreed to do some <hi>Horrid Act,</hi> and that the other <hi>One</hi> should oppose Them. A nefarious insinuation! to make our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Nations believe there's a <hi>Faction</hi> amongst our <hi>Judges:</hi> and that <hi>Eleven</hi> of them have <hi>Forfeited</hi> their <hi>Lives</hi> by going against the <hi>Law,</hi> and must therefore follow the <hi>Fate</hi> of <hi>Tresilion;</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:152706:14"/>
               <p>As for Sir <hi>Roberet Tresilian,</hi> and the rest of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Judges</hi> in the Reign of King <hi>Richard</hi> II. They came to be censur'd, not for their <hi>Loyal Advice</hi> to the <hi>King,</hi> but for giving him <hi>Contradictory Advice,</hi> and renouncing their first given Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel. <hi>Adulation</hi> in <hi>Future advice</hi> and Gross <hi>abuses</hi> of the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty,</hi> were those <hi>Judges Crimes.</hi> For it is Recorded in <hi>Stow, Baker,</hi> and others,— That Sir <hi>Robert Tresilian,</hi> and the rest of the <hi>Judges,</hi> had given the King <hi>Councel</hi> in his <hi>Parliament;</hi> and out of <hi>Parliament</hi> gave him <hi>advice</hi> quite contrary thereunto. Besides, Judge <hi>Tresilian</hi> is Noted for a Man of more <hi>Craft</hi> and <hi>Cruelty,</hi> than <hi>Justice</hi> and <hi>Integrity;</hi> and that at his coming to <hi>Coventry,</hi> he <hi>Indicted</hi> no less than 2000 Persons at once. An <hi>action</hi> sufficient to <hi>consternate</hi> the whole <hi>Kingdom.</hi> Nay, he was also in a <hi>Conspiracy</hi> with the Duke of <hi>Ireland,</hi> Earl of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> &amp;c. to destroy the Duke of <hi>Glocester,</hi> the <hi>Kings Uncle,</hi> and the most Powerful <hi>Subject</hi> of that Age. Thus the <hi>Indignation</hi> and <hi>Fury,</hi> not only of the <hi>Commonalty,</hi> but of the <hi>Gentry</hi> and <hi>Nobility</hi> likewise, came to be heightened against Sir <hi>Robert Tresilian,</hi> and the rest of the <hi>Judges</hi> of those days.</p>
               <p>But, what is all this to the Reverend <hi>Judges</hi> of our Time? What have <hi>They</hi> done that looks <hi>Parallel</hi> to the Actions of <hi>Tresilian?</hi> with whom have <hi>They</hi> Conspir'd? or against whom? What Countries have they injur'd? What <hi>Single person</hi> have <hi>They</hi> oppress'd? Or, wherein have <hi>They contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted Themselves,</hi> or given <hi>double</hi> Advice? Speak! Infamous <hi>Libeller!</hi> that <hi>They</hi> should be thus <hi>Menac'd</hi> with <hi>Tresilian?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>King</hi> could dispence with the <hi>Test,</hi> and all <hi>Laws.— 1.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HEre we meet with a Reflective <hi>Irony,</hi> and Gross <hi>False<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood</hi> together. The <hi>Libeller</hi> first <hi>Scoff's</hi> at the King's <hi>Dispensing</hi> Power, and then tells us, 'tis but <hi>One Year</hi> since He could <hi>dispense</hi> with <hi>all Laws.</hi>— If the <hi>King</hi> had not a <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spensing</hi> Power by virtue of His <hi>Prerogative Royal,</hi> the <hi>Subject</hi> were in a most unhappy <hi>Deplorable condition.</hi> As many of them must have sadly experienc'd, even since His Majesties <hi>access</hi> to His <hi>Throne,</hi> who, by due form of Law must have perished, had not the <hi>Royal Mercy</hi> interpos'd for their
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152706:14"/> Safety. <hi>Summum jus, Summa injunia.</hi> The Laws are strict; <hi>Malice</hi> of Enemies boundless; and many there are that delight to make a <hi>Man</hi> an <hi>Offender</hi> for a <hi>Word.</hi> The <hi>Judge</hi> and <hi>Jury</hi> go according to <hi>Evidence:</hi> and it is just they should do so. But suppose the <hi>Evidence</hi> to be a <hi>Plotting</hi> Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, whose <hi>Tongue</hi> is to be purchas'd by a <hi>Bribe;</hi> Or, what if he be a downright <hi>Enemy;</hi> He Swears for the <hi>King:</hi> The <hi>Prisoner</hi>'s Condemn'd, and (let him be never so Innocent) it is not in the Power of the <hi>Judge</hi> to Save him. We have had liberal <hi>Demonstration</hi> hereof in <hi>Otes's</hi> Reign. What think we now? What's fit to be done in so <hi>hard</hi> a Case? If the <hi>King,</hi> as Grand <hi>Trustee</hi> of all His <hi>Subjects Lives,</hi> have not a <hi>Dispensing Power,</hi> Envy and Falshood prevail, because given in <hi>Evidence, secondum Laegem,</hi> and an Honest Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent <hi>Subject</hi> is Lost. Certainly, in such a <hi>Case,</hi> both <hi>Reason</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> allow of a <hi>Dispensing Power</hi> in the <hi>King?</hi> Else He cannot be said to be exactly like <hi>God,</hi> whose <hi>Vicegerent</hi> He is, as wanting Power to extend <hi>Mercy</hi> to contemper and mitigate his <hi>Justice.</hi> And in my Opinion, none, but Men of <hi>Inhumane</hi> Dislloyal principles can any way grudge at it. Yea, but saith the <hi>Libeller,</hi> it is but <hi>One Year</hi> since the <hi>King</hi> could dispense with the <hi>TEST,</hi> and <hi>all Laws.</hi>— 'Tis the <hi>TEST</hi> you see, the <hi>Libeller</hi>'s in love with. The <hi>TEST!</hi> a <hi>Trick</hi> contriv'd by the <hi>Associating</hi> Party, to <hi>Exclude</hi> the <hi>Lawful Heir</hi> to the <hi>Crown.</hi> And, well may we question that Mans <hi>Loyalty</hi> to the <hi>King,</hi> that shall offer to <hi>plead</hi> for a continuance of the <hi>TEST,</hi> against His Majesties Royal Inclination: That, and the <hi>Covenant</hi> of 1643. being both <hi>design'd</hi> for the <hi>Ruine</hi> of the <hi>English Monarchy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But further, by the <hi>Libellers</hi> leave, the <hi>Dispensing</hi> Power is of more than <hi>One Years</hi> standing: Or else the good Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> could never have exercised it; nor any of the <hi>English Kings</hi> before, or since her time; which that they <hi>all did,</hi> both <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>History</hi> manifest. In cases of Life the <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Dispensing</hi> Power was never question'd. And, the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beller,</hi> when once the Law hath took hold of him for his <hi>Treasons,</hi> &amp;c. will be glad to <hi>own</hi> such a <hi>Prerogative;</hi> as sundry <hi>persons</hi> of late <hi>Years</hi> have done, to their peculiar
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152706:15"/>
                  <hi>Safety,</hi> and the <hi>Eternal Honour</hi> of His <hi>Majesties Courage</hi> and <hi>Clemency</hi> — Nay, our Learnedst Lawyers affirm, that not an <hi>Information,</hi> or <hi>Indictment</hi> upon Penal Statutes, but must give way to a <hi>Nolle prosequi,</hi> if the <hi>King</hi> please to move no further therein. And if it were not so, a <hi>Subject</hi> would usurp a <hi>Priveledge</hi> over his <hi>Sovereign,</hi> and make use of His <hi>Name</hi> without His leave (to sue in) for the <hi>vexing</hi> &amp; <hi>abusing</hi> whom he pleases. Than the which, there can be nothing more <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>just,</hi> or <hi>Unreasonable;</hi> nothing more <hi>absurd,</hi> and <hi>ridiculous.</hi> And so I have done with the <hi>Libellers</hi> Scandalous Lying Chronology.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>Libellers</hi> General Judgements brought to the <hi>Test</hi> and found unable to abide the <hi>Tryal</hi> of true <hi>Art</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN good time we are arrived at the <hi>Libellers General Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> wherein we shall <hi>meet</hi> with as much <hi>Loyalty, Truth</hi> and <hi>candour,</hi> as in the <hi>Former.</hi> He professes to build his <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions</hi> upon the <hi>Vernal Ingress</hi> of the Year; (a weak foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, when not supported by other more weighty Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.) But for want of room (he says) he forbears to insert the <hi>Scheam</hi> thereof. I will therefore do it for him, and shew him the Falseness thereof, and <hi>convince</hi> him of his persisting to abuse his <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Countrey</hi> under pretence of <hi>Astrology;</hi> whereas from the true <hi>Ingress,</hi> and other <hi>causes, Astrology</hi> speaks <hi>Good</hi> to both, and <hi>confusion</hi> to their <hi>Enemies.</hi> The <hi>Libeller,</hi> (though at <hi>Amsterdam</hi>) gives us the time of the <hi>Suns Ingress</hi> into <hi>Aries</hi> for <hi>London</hi> 1687. which is with him on <hi>March</hi> the 10th. day, at 10. Hours, 10 Minuits, <hi>A. M.</hi> the Figure's thus.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:152706:15"/>
               <figure>
                  <p>The LIBELLERS Figure for <hi>Sol</hi> entering <hi>Aries,</hi> 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7. <hi>March</hi> 10d. 10h. 10l. <hi>Mane.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sub. Latit. Londini.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>☽ a ☍ ♃ ad □ ☿</p>
                  <figDesc>astrological chart</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Behold the <hi>Craft</hi> of the <hi>Libeller!</hi> He makes use of a <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure</hi> from whence to draw his <hi>Judgements</hi> against his <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Countrey,</hi> that none of the <hi>Tables</hi> made by the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Masters in <hi>Astronomy</hi> will own. And thence he threatens the <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Sacred Life,</hi> and the <hi>Kingdoms Ruine,</hi> over-turning of the <hi>Government, Wars,</hi> &amp;c. and all this, and more, from a poor single <hi>Ingress</hi> of the <hi>Sun</hi> into <hi>Aries.</hi> But, alas! Doth not every <hi>Puny Astrologer</hi> know, that <hi>Vernal Figures,</hi> without consideration had to the Ruling <hi>Conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> and <hi>Aspects</hi> of the <hi>Stars</hi> at that time, are of very small or no <hi>Efficacy,</hi> from whence to Praedict <hi>Futurities.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I allow it for a <hi>Truth,</hi> that <hi>Mars</hi> in an <hi>Angle</hi> is <hi>per se,</hi> of violent signification, and is commonly attended with <hi>rugged
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152706:16"/> effects.</hi> It is no News to an <hi>Artist</hi> to hear <hi>Almansor</hi> Command Aphoristically.— <hi>Averte Oculos â Figura, in qua Mars fuerit in Angulo.</hi> And all <hi>Astrologers</hi> give <hi>Caution</hi> against the <hi>Heats</hi> of <hi>Mars.</hi> Which, the <hi>Libeller</hi> knowing, hath made a <hi>Scheam</hi> with <hi>Mars</hi> on an <hi>Angle</hi> (though a false one) that he might thence take occasion to <hi>affright</hi> and <hi>terrifie</hi> us the more easily. But, as his <hi>Figure</hi> is <hi>False,</hi> so are his <hi>Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> And were not <hi>Astronomy</hi> against him, yet the <hi>Events</hi> he expected have deceived him hitherto; and nothing hath happen'd to this <hi>Kingdom</hi> like to the furious Influence of <hi>Mars</hi> in an <hi>Angle,</hi> as he hath Praedicted.</p>
               <p>For further Eviction of his <hi>Errour</hi> herein, I shall present you with a <hi>true Figure</hi> of the Worlds Revolution for 1687, and that from such <hi>Tables Astronomical,</hi> as are in repute, and concurr with, the best and ablest <hi>Astronomers</hi> of the present Age. I say, the <hi>Tables</hi> of the <hi>Best Astronomers</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spire with the <hi>Figure</hi> I shall present you with, <hi>viz,</hi> the <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolphine, Billian, Bullialdine, Shackerleian</hi> Tables, and also those of <hi>Vincent Wing</hi> in his <hi>Astronomia Britannica,</hi> and many more; but none of them all do own the <hi>Libeller</hi>'s <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure.</hi> Perhaps he may have some singular conceited Author that himself only follows. But were it so, can any one force a belief upon me, that <hi>one Single Clock</hi> strikes the <hi>Hour</hi> of the <hi>Day</hi> true, when I find it <hi>differs</hi> vastly in <hi>Time</hi> from all the <hi>Famous</hi> and best made <hi>Clocks</hi> in the <hi>City?</hi> No sure. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides, I will tell the <hi>Libeller,</hi> that the certainty of <hi>Events</hi> do truly prove the <hi>Truth</hi> of <hi>Astronomy;</hi> and that there was an <hi>Astrology</hi> in the World, long before <hi>Astronomy</hi> came to any degree of Perfection; (perhaps before it was thought of,) as the <hi>Chaldean, Persian,</hi> and <hi>Jewish</hi> Philosophy fully prove. And <hi>Reason</hi> it self informs us, That had not Men first felt the <hi>Heats</hi> of <hi>Mars,</hi> and <hi>Cold</hi> of <hi>Saturn,</hi> it is very probable, they had never enquired after their <hi>Motions</hi> in the Heavens. <hi>Astronomy</hi> is therefore more oblig'd to <hi>Astrology</hi> than the World is aware of. And although the popular Opinion be, that <hi>Astronomy</hi> is the <hi>Elder</hi> Sister, (allowing <hi>Uraniah</hi> to have Twins) yet it is really the <hi>Younger;</hi> and <hi>Astrology</hi> hath the right of <hi>Primo-geniture.</hi> And so I come to give you the <hi>true Figure</hi> from the <hi>British Tables,</hi> thus.—</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:152706:16"/>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Tempus Datum, Ma.</hi> 9d. 20h. 15l. <hi>P. M.</hi> 1687.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Longit. Solis, S. d.</hi> ′. ″.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Apog. Solis. S. d</hi> ′ ″.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Longit. Med. Solis Apogaeo Solis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>11. 27. 58. 29. 3. 6. 57. 6.</cell>
                        <cell>3. 6. 57. 0.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Anomalia Solis.</hi>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>8. 21. 1. 23. 2. 1. 31.</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Verus locus Solis.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>0. 0. 0. 0.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>in. r.</hi> 0<hi>d.</hi> 0′. 0″.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And to this time, the</hi> Figure <hi>of Heaven in the</hi> Meridian <hi>of</hi> London, <hi>the</hi> Metropolis <hi>of</hi> England, <hi>is as followeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <figure>
                  <p>The true Figure of the <hi>Sun</hi> his entring <hi>Aries,</hi> 1687. <hi>March</hi> the 9d. 20g, 10l.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>P. M.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sub. Latit Londini.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>☽ â ☍ ♃ <hi>ad</hi> □ ☿</p>
                  <figDesc>astrological chart</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Here we have a <hi>Vernal Scheam</hi> of 1687. that somewhat resembles the happy Peaceable Actions of the Year. <hi>Jupiter,</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:152706:17"/> the most Benevolent Planet in the Heavens, is in the <hi>Seventh Angle,</hi> (the place of <hi>Discord, Controversy,</hi> &amp;c.) there posited as a <hi>Constable</hi> upon his <hi>Watch,</hi> keeping the Peace; or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as a good <hi>Christian Arbitrator,</hi> Uniting Persons or Kingdoms at Odds, and preventing any <hi>New</hi> Animosities to break forth▪ so far is he from giving any notice of <hi>Wars,</hi> or <hi>Controversies</hi> to happen, as the <hi>Libeller</hi> had assigned us from <hi>Mars</hi> on the <hi>Seventh</hi> in his false <hi>Figure.</hi> And yet we have <hi>Mars</hi> in <hi>Quadrate</hi> of the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Saturn,</hi> &amp;c. though in parts of Heaven less powerful to do mischief, then they were placed in, the <hi>Libellers</hi> Scheam. — Why, what a sad place is <hi>Holland,</hi> that cannot afford <hi>one Astrologer</hi> able to Correct the <hi>Falshoods</hi> and <hi>Scandals</hi> of this Pitiful <hi>Libeller,</hi> that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habits among them.</p>
               <p>Before I proceed any further, I will in pure pity, teach this <hi>Libeller</hi> a little <hi>Art,</hi> that he may better <hi>Con</hi> his Lesson against the next year; for then he promises to appear again, <hi>viz.</hi> After he hath Learn'd a little <hi>good Manners,</hi> and aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd <hi>Disloyalty</hi> and <hi>Treason;</hi> (before which I shall never allow him to set up for a <hi>Secretary</hi> of the <hi>Stars.</hi>) Then let him <hi>supplicate</hi> God Almighty for his Grace and Assistance, in the Discovery of <hi>Truth;</hi> as the Noble <hi>Arabians</hi> were wont always to do. And when he hath thus fitted himself for his Work, making his entrance thereunto <hi>In Nomine Dei;</hi> He'll never think it just and honest to make a Noble <hi>Art</hi> a <hi>Bawd</hi> or <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty</hi> whereby to Praedict <hi>Wars,</hi> and <hi>Destruction</hi> to his <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Countrey;</hi> but follow the <hi>true</hi> Principles of <hi>Science,</hi> and acquaint us with the truth of the <hi>Stars</hi> Portents to us.</p>
               <p>But if he will not take this <hi>advice,</hi> as there's but little hopes he will; then I admonish him (for the better favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his hard favour'd <hi>Presages,</hi>) that if he find <hi>Mars</hi> in a Qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rupcian or <hi>Beastial Sign,</hi> he do not make him dart all his <hi>Influence</hi> upon <hi>Humane</hi> kind; but remember that the <hi>Stars</hi> Operate upon such kind of <hi>creatures</hi> only, as are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presented by the <hi>Signs</hi> they possess. The <hi>Libeller</hi> knew, that <hi>Mars, Sol,</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> (in his own Figure) were not lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated in <hi>Humane Signs,</hi> and therefore could not Influence <hi>Men</hi> with any remarkable <hi>Violence</hi> in this Revolution —
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152706:17"/> The Superiour Planet <hi>Saturn</hi> ('tis true) is in a <hi>Humane</hi> Sign. But, Sir, he is not an <hi>Enemy,</hi> but a <hi>Friend</hi> both to the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Commonalty,</hi> forasmuch as he irradiates both <hi>Medium Coeli;</hi> and the <hi>Horoscope,</hi> with an Amicable Aspect; and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights and rejoyces in both places, as being Eminently Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified in them, He cannot therefore countenance any of the <hi>Dismal Praesages</hi> which the <hi>Libeller</hi> hath <hi>Falsly</hi> scatter'd among us. Nay, to our Comfort, and the <hi>Libellers</hi> Shame, we see the <hi>Year</hi> near three parts expir'd, and <hi>Nothing</hi> hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto of his <hi>Praedictions</hi> have come to pass; nor is there any doubt but that they'l be answer'd with the same <hi>success</hi> in the remaining Quarter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>But now enter <hi>Libeller.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <q>THis Position <hi>(meaning his own false Figure,)</hi> taken in general, is violent and pernicious; for it shews the Clergy and Commonalty of <hi>England</hi> to be at variance, and to look on each other with an ill aspect; and to say the Truth, the People cannot well have a good opinion of them; for it was They that pull'd in <hi>Popery</hi> by preaching up that cursed Doctrine of passive Obedience.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Caitiff</hi> cannot breath out a <hi>Praediction</hi> without some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the <hi>Incendiary</hi> and <hi>Traytor.</hi>— He knows the true Figure of the Ingress of <hi>Sol</hi> in <hi>Aries</hi> 1687. owns nothing of all this Scurrilous Treasonable <hi>Menace.</hi> Let us examine it a little, and that by <hi>Authority;</hi> a way the <hi>Libeller</hi> scorns to make use of. Indeed, <hi>Authors</hi> are against him. Here <hi>Haly▪ Si</hi> Jupiter <hi>fuerit in septima domo fortunatus,</hi> (as he must needs be when in <hi>Sagitary) gaudebunt homines mulieribus, &amp; mulieres hominibus,</hi> &amp;c. (i e.) When the Benevolent Planet <hi>Jupiter</hi> in a Revolutional Figure of the World, shall be fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately placed in the <hi>Seventh Angle,</hi> Men and Women in that Revolution shall rejoyce promiscuously together, and there shall be much <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Quiet</hi> among them. No Plotting and Contriving to do mischief can then take any effect: The Stars <hi>(sub Deo)</hi> renders the <hi>Malice</hi> of Enemies fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate. Nay, <hi>Jupiter</hi> so located— <hi>Significat multum bonum in anni medietate, &amp; meliorem successem in arboribus &amp; fructus multos.</hi> He signifies much good to Humane kind to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152706:18"/> the middle of the Revolution, chiefly, (the <hi>Seventh Angle</hi> divides the Circle with the Horoscope,) and that the Honest <hi>Husband-man,</hi> or <hi>Farmer,</hi> shall have better success in his <hi>Gardens, Orchards,</hi> and in his Setting and Planting, than in former years, and that they shall yield him abundance of <hi>Fruit,</hi> &amp;c. rewarding of his Sweat and pains, to his great Content and Satisfaction.</p>
               <p>Let now Experience be Judge! When ever had we a more <hi>Peaceable, calm,</hi> and <hi>Quiet Year!</hi> When were we bless'd with geater <hi>Plenty</hi> of <hi>Fruit</hi> and <hi>Herbage?</hi> as if it were an Earnest of the favour of Heaven, in removing from us the <hi>Meagre-Sower</hi> effects which the late <hi>terrible Frost</hi> had left behind it. When had we fewer <hi>Law Suits</hi> in a year? Or, when, in <hi>Term time,</hi> was <hi>Westminster-Hall</hi> ever less throng'd? And is not all this parallel to the Position of <hi>Jupiter</hi> in the <hi>Seventh Angle?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But we have not only <hi>Jupiter</hi> in the Seventh Angle, but the <hi>Moon</hi> in the <hi>Horoscope;</hi> (and the <hi>Moon,</hi> we know, is to be valued as more than half the <hi>Figure,</hi> she being the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigher of all the other <hi>Planets</hi> Influences to us.) When <hi>God Almighty</hi> graciously vouchsafes to befriend either <hi>Nations</hi> or <hi>Persons,</hi> He is pleas'd to suit Natural Causes thereunto accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly! 'Tis not in every <hi>Mundane Figure</hi> we have <hi>Jupiter</hi> in the Seventh, or the <hi>Moon</hi> in the <hi>Horoscope,</hi> 'Tis his great Mercy to our undeserving <hi>Nation,</hi> we find them so now.— The <hi>Moon</hi> in the <hi>Horoscope,</hi> being in a <hi>Humane Sign,</hi> denotes much happiness and success to <hi>Men,</hi> and not <hi>Wars</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusions,</hi> as the <hi>Libeller</hi> talks of; nor yet <hi>Quarrels</hi> between the <hi>Clergy</hi> and <hi>Commonalty,</hi> about pulling in <hi>Popery,</hi> by their Preaching up <hi>Passive Obedience,</hi> of which, more anon.— What says our Noble <hi>Arabian</hi> thereunto? <hi>Quando Luna est in Ascendente, significat prosperitatem &amp; Salvationem Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li in suis corporibus, &amp; in omnibus membris suis,</hi> When the <hi>Moon</hi> shall be scituate in the <hi>ascendant,</hi> (chiefly in a <hi>Humane</hi> Sign) much Prosperity and Felicity is portended to the <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> generally in that year, Security to their Estates, Health to their Persons; and that they shall be vigorous and strong in all parts, sound and free from any Malignant Distempers.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:152706:18"/>
               <p>Let any sober observing <hi>Artist,</hi> or Other, tell me— Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this Judgement be not true in every part of it. Hath it not been a <hi>Gentle</hi> and <hi>Prosperous</hi> year with us hitherto? have we not enjoy'd <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Plenty</hi> in all things? Nay, in the thing that is most dear to us, I mean, <hi>a quiet Enjoyment of Peace of Conscience in our Religious Worship?</hi> And as to Corporal Health, we have been wonderfully blessed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with hitherto. When was it known, that the <hi>City</hi> hath had more People in it, and that the <hi>Bills</hi> of <hi>Mortality</hi> have been so <hi>moderate?</hi>— All proving against the <hi>Libeller,</hi> that his Figure and Judgements too, are notoriously False.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Libeller</hi> goes on threat'ning,— <hi>page</hi> 2. Mercury <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der "the</hi> Sun <hi>Beams brings the Curse of Diseases,</hi> &amp;c. But I tell him, that <hi>Mercury</hi> (even by his own Figure) hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do with <hi>Diseases.</hi> He might, (indeed) (had his Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure been true) have a hand in the <hi>Cure</hi> of <hi>Diseases,</hi> but not in the <hi>Cause</hi> of them. This malicious <hi>Trifter</hi> understands not the very first <hi>Principles</hi> of <hi>Astrology,</hi> but makes a <hi>Blundering</hi> with what comes uppermost, without either <hi>Reason</hi> or <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi> I desire him for time to come, to remember, that the <hi>Sixth</hi> is <hi>Domus Infirmitatum,</hi> and that the <hi>Tenth</hi> is <hi>Domus Medicinae,</hi> and not think to <hi>Pawn</hi> and <hi>Shuffle</hi> such apparent <hi>Falshoods</hi> upon the World for <hi>Truth:</hi> As if every Man that read him, understood nothing of the Significations, or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinctions of the <hi>Twelve Angles</hi> of Heaven.</p>
               <p>But the <hi>Libeller</hi> seems to lay the weight of his Forged False Praedictions upon the <hi>Moons</hi> being in opposition to <hi>Jupiter,</hi> saying;— <q>The <hi>Moon,</hi> if you consider her Latitude, is not full twenty one Degrees in <hi>Gemini,</hi> and applying to an Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position of Jupiter.</q>— And thence it is he hath presumed to set the <hi>Clergy</hi> and <hi>Commonalty</hi> together by the <hi>Ears,</hi> for their Preaching up the Doctrine of <hi>Passive Obedience,</hi> and bringing in <hi>Popery.</hi> But that <hi>Aspest</hi> (the same in his False, as well as in the True Figure) is wholly against him, and gives him no countenance at all; for Reasons I have given in my Examen of his <hi>Monthly Errours.</hi> And, although I have neither <hi>Time</hi> nor <hi>Room,</hi> to cite Authors at large for his Conviction; (as in truth it needs not) yet, I'll Summon <hi>Haly</hi> in this Point, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:152706:19"/> If the <hi>Moon</hi> shall (in any Revolution) apply <hi>ad oppositum</hi> Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis, <hi>significat placita &amp; verba in lege &amp; ejus Scientia,</hi> &amp;c. And now let the <hi>Libeller</hi> tell me, whether this Oppositions Influence, looks like a difference between the <hi>Clergy</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty</hi> for their pulling in of <hi>Popery,</hi> by their Preaching the <hi>accursed Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Passive Obedience.</hi> As he <hi>accursedly</hi> calls it.— But, have the <hi>English Clergy</hi> pull'd in <hi>Popery</hi> in earnest? Are they the <hi>Friends</hi> to it as this Man asserts? Is it really <hi>Settled</hi> yet among us? Let the <hi>Libeller</hi> reckon again, and calmly, and he'll find for one <hi>Catholick Chappel,</hi> an hundred <hi>Conventicles.</hi> He need not therefore make <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery</hi> the <hi>Bugbear</hi> wherewith to affright the <hi>Nation.</hi> The <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beller</hi>'s angry, that the poor <hi>Catholicks,</hi> (after their having been <hi>Harass'd, Imprison'd, Plunder'd,</hi> by such as <hi>Waller</hi> and his <hi>Crew;</hi> and suffer'd so miserably in their <hi>Lives, Liberties,</hi> and <hi>Estates;</hi> yea so severely, that had they dwelt among <hi>Turks,</hi> they could scarce have been worse used;) should par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take at all of His <hi>Majesties</hi> Universal <hi>Favour</hi> to His <hi>Subjects;</hi> forgetting it seems, that they are <hi>English-men,</hi> as much as any of the other <hi>Dissenters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But alas! I do not so much wonder that this <hi>Uncharitable</hi> Wretch, (like another <hi>Julian Johnson</hi>) doth <hi>Storm</hi> and <hi>Rail</hi> at the Doctrine of <hi>Passive Obedience</hi> (he being, as he thinks, safe at <hi>Amsterdam,</hi>) when I find some of far greater Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Breadth in the World, (pretended <hi>Advocates</hi> for the Doctrine▪) to declaim as Zealously against it. Pray here <hi>One</hi> of them, for All, in an <hi>Address</hi> to <hi>Julian,</hi> viz. <q>Be it known to Mr. <hi>J. (i. e.</hi> Mr. <hi>Johnson</hi>) that many of those who have Thunder'd so much of late with the <hi>Thebaean Legion,</hi> would rather think it their Duty, than any breach of it to tell, not only a <hi>Popish Prince,</hi> but a <hi>Popish King</hi> to His Face, did He openly profess the <hi>Popish Religion,</hi> that He was an Idolater, a Bread-Worshipper, a Goddess-worshipper, an Image-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipper, a Wafer-wroshipper, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Jovian <hi>p. 96.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Here's the Doctrine of <hi>Passive Obedience</hi> made out with a witness! What greater <hi>Affront</hi> can be offer'd to <hi>God?</hi> to <hi>Religion?</hi> to the <hi>King?</hi> Is all our pretence and claim to the right of <hi>Primo-geniture</hi> in <hi>Loyalty,</hi> come to this? Is to <hi>Rail,</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:152706:19"/> and <hi>Resist;</hi> become the Doctrine of <hi>Non-resistance?</hi> Is <hi>pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive Obedience</hi> turn'd into the <hi>Bearding</hi> and <hi>Upbraiding</hi> of <hi>Kings?</hi> Heaven help us! Where are we?— My <hi>Province</hi> is not <hi>Divinity,</hi> and therefore I forbear. But this Authors <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy,</hi> and the Libellers <hi>Astrology,</hi> are of a stamp both for <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Art,</hi> and <hi>Loyalty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To return to our <hi>Libeller</hi> again, for 'tis He I have chiefly to do with. In <hi>page</hi> 2. he Praedicts,— <q>The People of that Nation <hi>(England)</hi> shall again take Courage, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lease themselves from the Oppressions they now labour under, and this in a few Months; for it doth not reach unto Years.</q> And this Judgement he derives from the <hi>Square</hi> of <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Mercury.</hi>
                  <q>who, <hi>(says he)</hi> are the two Stars that Pers<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate the King and Government.- <hi>Mercury</hi> is under <hi>the Sun-Beams,</hi> which shews the Curse of Diseases. and <hi>Jupiter</hi> is in a Zodaical Parallel with <hi>Mars,</hi> which shews want of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and also Danger of Death. These plainly shew a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tastrophy approaching, and that there will be a change in that Kingdom and Government also, and this in a short time.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Thus far this dating <hi>Incendiary,</hi> with design to Buoy up the sinking hopes of <hi>Rebels</hi> and <hi>Traytors,</hi> in expectation of the <hi>Ruine</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> to be near at hand, <hi>viz.</hi> in a <hi>few Months, for it doth not reach unto Years,</hi> he says. But to manifest this to be a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ry vain and feigned encouragement to his <hi>own Party,</hi> (who I wish no longer to credit his <hi>Falshoods,</hi> but return to their <hi>Obedience,</hi>) the very Configuration upon which he builds all this <hi>Treasonous Trash,</hi> (which is the <hi>Quadrate</hi> of <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Mercury,</hi>) is of a quite opposite signification. Once more hear <hi>Haly,</hi>— If <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> shall (in any Mundane Revolution) be in a <hi>Quadrate</hi> Aspect of each other, and that this Aspect shall happen from the <hi>Tenth Angle,</hi> (as it doth in his own false Figure,) <hi>Signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t quod Reges diligent multum scire &amp; perquirere Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias, &amp; amabunt libros,</hi> &amp;c. Such a Position and Aspect (saith he) denotes that <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> shall desire to know and read much, and diligently enquire into <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Sciences,</hi> that They shall be in love with <hi>Books,</hi> and will
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152706:20"/> greatly incline to <hi>Learning,</hi> and to be acquainted with the <hi>Mysteries</hi> of sundry curious Subtilties, the Secrets of Wisdom, and the like.</p>
               <p>This should honestly have been his Judgement from his own false Figure: Of which the <hi>Libeller</hi> was either Ignorant, or else had no mind his own Friends (with whom he basely prevaricates) should know the truth of things.</p>
               <p>But now, in the <hi>true</hi> Vernal Scheam, we meet with a much better signification of this <hi>Aspect:</hi> For therein we find <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury</hi> in the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Angle of <hi>Friendship, As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance,</hi> and of the <hi>Good Spirit;</hi> and there, being in <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drate</hi> of <hi>Jupiter, Astrologers</hi> tell us, he signifies— <hi>Quod Rex vocabitur ad se sapientes, &amp; ornabit eos.</hi> This Excellent <hi>As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect</hi> gives us great hopes of much happiness to attend the Kingdom of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Governour</hi> thereof, and seems to intimate <hi>(sub Deo)</hi> that His <hi>Majesty</hi> will call unto Himself the Assistance, Aid, &amp; Advise of the most Wise and Learned <hi>Men</hi> both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> and will Heap, or Confer Honours and Priviledges upon them according to their Capacity, Dignity, or Merit. It is of so Favourable an Influence to these Nations, (considering the <hi>Moon</hi> in <hi>Gemini,</hi> in <hi>Trine</hi> of the Eleventh Angle, and Aspect of <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Mercury,</hi> as before) that if it shall please God to incline His Sacred Majesty to call a <hi>Parliament,</hi> (His great Council of the Realm!) It may prove a most Happy and Healing As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly to both the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> such a <hi>Parliament,</hi> whose great Wisdom may be made use of to Settle these Kingdoms in a fixed Condition of Prosperity, Peace, and Plenty, to the wonder of after Ages; and which we hope will consider of, and advise the Enacting of such Provisional Laws for a continuance thereof, as shall make for the <hi>Kings Honour,</hi> and for the <hi>Terrour</hi> of His and the Kingdoms <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies;</hi> and also be able to reach all wicked <hi>Traytors</hi> and <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellers,</hi> tho' lurking in <hi>Holes</hi> beyond the <hi>Seas,</hi> thence trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting their <hi>Treas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nous</hi> and <hi>Blasphemous</hi> Papers hither to do mischief.</p>
               <p>These are the Natural significations of that <hi>Quadrate Aspect,</hi> upon which the Traducer excites his Native Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152706:20"/> to a <hi>Rebellion,</hi> by telling them— <hi>They shall again take Courage, and Release themselves,</hi>— Ha! Take Courage! Against whom?— Release themselves! from what? The <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beller,</hi> would have been a happy Man, no doubt, had he lived in <hi>Cromwels,</hi> the Usurpers <hi>time.</hi> For then was <hi>Astrology</hi> made a <hi>Pander</hi> and <hi>Property</hi> to every <hi>Treasonous purpose</hi> in the World: <hi>Art</hi> was wrested, Judgement from the Stars <hi>Forged;</hi> and all to encourage <hi>Rebels</hi> on the one hand, and terrifie <hi>Loyal Persons</hi> on the other. The Knavish Republi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans, then, as now, making it the Burden of their <hi>Song,</hi> to open against <hi>Monarchy.</hi> Take Courage! Release your selves! He tells you plainly against whom, and from what? if you dare take his word, in his Treasonable Verses to the Honest <hi>Protestants,</hi> thus,—
<q>
                     <l>The <hi>Sun</hi> will Rise, the <hi>Actors</hi> fill the <hi>Stage,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And <hi>One and Twenty Months</hi> is not an Age.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Again.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Now <hi>Hangs</hi> your <hi>Freedom</hi> on each <hi>Villains</hi> Sword,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cheated</hi> your Selves, taking your <hi>Princes</hi> Word.</l>
               </q>
               <p>And in his Farewel he says,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> Commonwealth<hi>'s the thing that</hi> Kingdoms <hi>want.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Libeller</hi> can't be thought here to speak in <hi>Riddles,</hi> like the Devil of <hi>Delphos.</hi> But will he say he deduces these Ryming <hi>Scandals</hi> from the Heavens too? I would have him, or any of the Rebellious Tribe he belongs to, set Spleen and Rancour aside, and soberly ask the <hi>Nation,</hi>— Whether it ever enjoy'd a more <hi>Free, Tranquile,</hi> and <hi>Peaceable</hi> time, than since His present <hi>Sacred Majesties</hi> access to the <hi>Throne</hi> of His <hi>Ancestors?</hi> (abating <hi>Monmouths</hi> Rebellion.) Does not every Man sit under his own <hi>Vine,</hi> and Eat the Fruit of his own <hi>Fig-tree,</hi> or Labour without disturbance? Do we not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy both <hi>Life</hi> (and its Comforts) <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Property,</hi> in a far greater measure than in any Age preceding? We are not annoy'd with <hi>Informers</hi> or <hi>Catch-poles,</hi> or with vexatious <hi>Suits</hi> or <hi>Indictments</hi> for our <hi>Religion.</hi> We have no <hi>Taxes</hi> to burden us. No Man permitted to do us wrong. The Law is preserved in its just <hi>Current</hi> (its rigour only abated; and is there any harm in that?) and <hi>awards</hi> to every one his <hi>Right</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:152706:21"/> What is it that he would have Men take <hi>Courage</hi> against? What is it (I say) this <hi>Libeller</hi> would be <hi>Released</hi> from? When they groan under <hi>no Oppression</hi> at all; Are <hi>Burthen'd</hi> with nothing; except with an <hi>Excess</hi> of <hi>Ease</hi> and <hi>Plenty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh! <hi>English-men!</hi> ye know not the <hi>happiness</hi> you enjoy under a Lawful and <hi>Religious Monarch! Holland</hi> it self (the place that protects this <hi>Libeller</hi>) is, in comparison of <hi>England,</hi> a <hi>Hell</hi> to the <hi>Subject;</hi> where he cannot so much as wear a <hi>pair of Shooes,</hi> or eat an <hi>Herring,</hi> before they be <hi>nine times. Excis'd.</hi> As the Ingeniously Learned Sir <hi>George Pudsey</hi> most truly and wisely observ'd in his <hi>Speech</hi> at <hi>Oxford,</hi> upon his being admitted the worthy <hi>Recorder</hi> of that <hi>City.</hi> Whereas We of this <hi>Nation,</hi> like the <hi>Jews</hi> with <hi>Quails</hi> in our mouths, invoke the Wrath of God by <hi>Railing</hi> against His Majesty and His Government. We have <hi>Surfeited</hi> of <hi>Freedom,</hi> and like <hi>Jesurun,</hi> being waxed Fat, are ever ready, not only to <hi>Diso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey,</hi> but <hi>Kick</hi> at our <hi>Superiours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the <hi>Libeller</hi> hath studied the <hi>Case</hi> more fully, and as <hi>boldly</hi> as plainly, tells us, what we are <hi>defective</hi> in, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>Commonwealth</hi>'s the thing that <hi>Kingdoms</hi> want.</p>
               <p>I believe, the <hi>Libeller</hi> would, (<hi>non obstante</hi> this Bravado) give all the <hi>Shooes</hi> in his Shop to be at home quietly again, and be <hi>acquit</hi> of his <hi>Commonwealth.</hi>— But he shapes well, to make us believe the contrary; and gives his Brethren hopes of a <hi>Change</hi> in <hi>England;</hi> and <hi>page</hi> 4. thus Salutes us.— <q>
                     <hi>England</hi> seems to be pointed at in particular, as you may easily see, if you do but consider <hi>Aries</hi> as <hi>Englands</hi> Horoscope, and <hi>Gemini</hi> as <hi>Londons.</hi> And thus will there be turning, and overturning, till the Great turn comes.</q> Quod faxit Deus,</p>
               <p>Incarnate Devil! to invoke God to hasten a <hi>Rebellion</hi> which himself (without ground in <hi>Art) praedicts.</hi> What if <hi>Aries</hi> be the <hi>Horoscope</hi> of <hi>England?</hi> It is not so particularly at this time. But, what if it were? Is not <hi>Venus</hi> in it? Doth not <hi>England</hi> dispose of its <hi>Enemies Significator,</hi> and (by his own words) <hi>afflict</hi> her too? And, what if <hi>Gemini</hi> be <hi>Londons</hi> Horoscope at large? Is not the <hi>Franchises</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of seized into the <hi>Kings Hands?</hi> You know for what, <hi>Libel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler!</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:152706:21"/> And a particular <hi>Horoscope</hi> of that Famous <hi>City,</hi> no Man can know until His Majesty of His Grace give them a New <hi>Charter▪</hi> which (finding the <hi>Moon</hi> in <hi>Gemini</hi>) I hope the Noble <hi>Senators</hi> thereof, by their <hi>Grave, Prudent,</hi> and <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Actions</hi> and Demeanours towards their <hi>Sovereign Lord,</hi> will incline His <hi>Majesty</hi> the sooner to take it into His Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Consideration.</p>
               <p>But, how comes the <hi>Libeller</hi> to be now so zealous for a <hi>Commonwealth?</hi> When, not long since, he contended as ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly for <hi>Monarchy,</hi> provided the unhappy <hi>Monmouth</hi> had been the <hi>Man.</hi> But possibly he deems an <hi>Illegitimate</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, and a <hi>Commonwealth</hi> Synonyma's. No matter which to him, so a <hi>Change</hi> come, that he may get by the <hi>Bargain.</hi> Any thing but the <hi>Legal Heir</hi> will please his Pallate.— And, herein the <hi>Libeller</hi> Eccho's to a couple of <hi>English</hi> Miscre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants, calling themselves <hi>Astrologers</hi> also, who have <hi>Printed</hi> nearly the like <hi>Scandalous</hi> and <hi>Treasonable Stuff,</hi> some years since, under pretence of <hi>Praedictions. vid. Holwel</hi>'s <hi>Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strophe mundi,</hi> page 61. And <hi>Kirby</hi>'s <hi>Astrological Prophet.</hi> page 29.</p>
               <p>But this Ternary of <hi>Knaves</hi> and <hi>Impostors</hi> have all liv'd to see themselves mistaken, by a Lawful <hi>Monarch</hi>'s taking place against their long-hop'd for <hi>Commonwealth</hi> Nay. I dare assure the <hi>Libeller,</hi> and all that thirst for a <hi>Dem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>crati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal change,</hi> that the <hi>Stars</hi> are against them; and (if they be not willfully blind) they may plainly see, that <hi>God,</hi> (who is greater than the <hi>Stars,</hi>) is also against them too; and they will be all most miserably deceived and deluded in their Expectation thereof. Alas! A <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> (that is a <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> with no <hi>Head,</hi> or with many <hi>Heads</hi>) will not go down here. This <hi>Nation,</hi> Mad as it hath been (and the <hi>Libeller</hi> wishes it so agai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, hath <hi>try'd,</hi> not only this <hi>Experiment,</hi> but all other <hi>Governments,</hi> and disrelish'd them all, but <hi>Monarchy.</hi> It hath had <hi>Presidials, Viceg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rents, Lieutenant, Generals, Parliaments,</hi> a <hi>Free-State, Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tectors, Major-Generals, Committee of Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> &amp;c. But how uncouth, uneasy, and disgustful <hi>All</hi> of them have been to the three <hi>Nations,</hi> let the whole World about us <hi>Judge;</hi> who have with wonder and amazement beheld
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152706:22"/> our <hi>Confusions.</hi> All which <hi>mutations</hi> plainly tell us, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can <hi>agree</hi> to the Honour and Government of these <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Nation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> but a <hi>Legal</hi> Crowned Head.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Britannia ab initio mundi semper fuit Regia, &amp; Regimen illius simile ille Coelorum,</hi> (saith one.) Great <hi>Britain</hi> from the beginning of the World hath been <hi>Kingly,</hi> and her <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> like to that of the <hi>Heavens.</hi> It is impossible (I say) therefore, that she can remain long in <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Quiet</hi> under any other <hi>Power.</hi> And, what if I should tell you that <hi>Ptole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> (that great Master of <hi>Astrology</hi>) hath plac'd <hi>England</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Aries,</hi> a <hi>Kingly Sign,</hi> and the very first of the <hi>Fiery Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon,</hi> as well as of the <hi>Zodiack.</hi> A Sign, wherein the <hi>Sun</hi> (the true representer of <hi>Kings</hi>) receives his <hi>Exaltation.</hi> As if it had been the <hi>Decree</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Kings</hi> (according to the Order of the <hi>Stars</hi>) that nothing but a <hi>Monarchy</hi> should be suitable to this Kingly <hi>Nation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I wonder how any Man endu'd with <hi>Reason,</hi> can plead for a <hi>Commonwealth?</hi> If he consider his <hi>Creation,</hi> that, as he is a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or a <hi>little World,</hi> and had but <hi>One Head</hi> as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign'd him, therein made in the <hi>Image</hi> of Him who is <hi>Lord</hi> of the <hi>Universe,</hi> he cannot possibly but own a <hi>Monarchy</hi> before all other Powers If <hi>God</hi> had intended a <hi>Man</hi> should have been in <hi>Love</hi> with a <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> he would have Created him with a <hi>Head</hi> on each <hi>Shoulder,</hi> as well as with what he did make him, which renders him of <hi>Form</hi> and <hi>Figure</hi> plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant and graceful; whereas the <hi>other</hi> had been to have made him in the <hi>Image</hi> of <hi>Cerberus,</hi> and not of that <hi>Wise</hi> and <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Being</hi> whose shadow he truly is. If <hi>Government</hi> therefore, like the <hi>Body Natural,</hi> should have <hi>many Heads,</hi> 'tis a <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> and we know it ever bodes <hi>III.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And, will not a dear-bought <hi>Experience</hi> convince us of this <hi>Gross Errour</hi> yet? And when we have <hi>paid</hi> so fully for our Knowledge? Is there any need of more <hi>Suns</hi> than one in a <hi>Day?</hi> Or of more <hi>Moons</hi> than one in a <hi>Night?</hi> Or of one <hi>King</hi> in a <hi>Kingdom?</hi> I cannot but think that Man out of his wits (saith one) that would affirm a positive necessity of any more. Hath not <hi>England</hi> been <hi>Fleec'd</hi> for its <hi>Wantonness</hi> and <hi>Wickedness?</hi> We thirsted after <hi>Change</hi> in 1641. we obtain'd
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152706:22"/> it But what got we by it? <hi>Ruine</hi> and <hi>Destruction.</hi> And that will be our <hi>Portion</hi> again, in case we should turn <hi>Wanton</hi> again. Hath not this Glorious <hi>Nation,</hi> first by <hi>opposing,</hi> and afterwards <hi>murdering</hi> the best of <hi>Kings,</hi> been turn'd into an <hi>Aceldema?</hi> And were we not made thereby the <hi>scorn</hi> and <hi>by- word</hi> of all the <hi>Nations</hi> round about us? Have not our state<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Pallaces</hi> and most Glorious <hi>Structures</hi> been turn'd into <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solation</hi> and <hi>Rubbish?</hi> Our <hi>Plenty</hi> into <hi>Penury?</hi> Our <hi>Free-Trading</hi> into Dangerous <hi>Hazards?</hi>— And whereas, while under a <hi>Monarchy</hi> we sate <hi>quietly,</hi> (as now we do, <hi>Laus Deo,</hi>) and enjoy'd our <hi>Peace, Liberty</hi> and <hi>Property.</hi> Lo! when we were Subject to the <hi>Tyrany</hi> of a <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> (a <hi>Headles<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> or a <hi>Hydra-Government!</hi>) the Bramble of <hi>Confusion</hi> was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually <hi>scratching</hi> and <hi>tearing</hi> us.— Oh! what <hi>Virtuous things</hi> have <hi>Free-Quarter! publick Faith! Meal-money! De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimation!</hi> Robbing <hi>poor Servants</hi> of their <hi>Bodkins</hi> and <hi>Thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles! Composition</hi> over and over! And <hi>One hundred and twenty thousand pounds per mensem!</hi> I say, what <hi>Virtuous things</hi> have these been to <hi>England,</hi> in comparison of a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vial Story of <hi>Ship-money!</hi> Which was indeed the <hi>No Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance</hi> that was Rebelliously complain'd of in the year 1640. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That <hi>Fatal year!</hi> in which <hi>Monarchy</hi> began first to be <hi>Bearded</hi> in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By this short <hi>System</hi> of our past <hi>miseries,</hi> occasion'd by a <hi>Few</hi> Factious Spirits at the first, we may see, and be convinc'd, (if we are not willfully blind with obstinate prejudice) that the <hi>little Finger</hi> of a <hi>Commonwealth</hi> is <hi>Heavier</hi> than a <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch</hi>'s <hi>Loyns.</hi> But the <hi>Libeller</hi> being of another Opinion, tells us,—
<q>Now, Hangs our <hi>Freedom</hi> on each <hi>Villains</hi> Sword</q>
               </p>
               <p>This is a brisk gird at his <hi>Majesty</hi> for keeping an <hi>Army</hi> for the Security and Peace of the <hi>Kingdom.</hi> He'd be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that the <hi>KING</hi> were without a <hi>Guard,</hi> and <hi>Naked,</hi> that he, and his <hi>Party</hi> may the more easily <hi>Seize</hi> Him, and <hi>bind</hi> Him in <hi>chains.</hi> But the <hi>Libeller</hi> may ask, as some of his <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> formerly,— <hi>Are not the Train'd-Bands a Gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rd sufficient for His</hi> Majesty <hi>and the Kingdoms peace?</hi> I answer, no! Our late <hi>Wectern Experience</hi> tells him, no! Every one who can
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152706:23"/> wield a Pike, hath not the Valour to resist a Multitude of Evil Doers; hath not the <hi>Education</hi> to distinguish a <hi>Good Title</hi> to the <hi>Crown,</hi> nor a Resolution great enough to <hi>abet</hi> it. <hi>Jack Straw</hi> and <hi>Wat Tyler</hi> shew what Service the <hi>Countrey Train'd-Bands</hi> can do, when led on blindfold to pull down what they ought to maintain. So there is need of an <hi>Army,</hi> and why not? Doth not His Majesty pay them? <hi>Order</hi> them? and where need is, shew them the <hi>Severiiy</hi> of the <hi>Law?</hi> Upon this Coercive Power thus Establish'd;— Whose <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties</hi> have they Invaded? Or what <hi>Damage</hi> have any suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd by this, I may say, <hi>Civiliz'd Army?</hi> (unless he'll call that of opposing <hi>Monmouth</hi> in the <hi>West,</hi> a Damage.) An <hi>Army</hi> for Order and Discipline, none ever saw a <hi>better.</hi> Their <hi>Camp</hi> being more like a <hi>Well-Govern'd City,</hi> than a <hi>Field of Mars</hi> I am assured none can truly affirm that any <hi>one man</hi> in the Countrey where they came, hath been wrong'd to the value of a <hi>Pig, Goose, Hen,</hi> or an <hi>Egg,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Redress,</hi> in case complaint have been duly made against the <hi>Offender<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> We Honour and Value the <hi>Train'd-Bands,</hi> &amp;c. had they nothing else to mind but the <hi>Service</hi> of His <hi>Majesty,</hi> and <hi>Safety</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom.</hi> But <hi>Wives</hi> and <hi>Families</hi> are grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Clogs</hi> to <hi>Clergy-men</hi> and <hi>Souldiers,</hi> than to others. They are Powerful <hi>Load-Stones</hi> to draw Mens <hi>affections!</hi> of the <hi>One</hi> from the True <hi>Service</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>Other</hi> from the Faithful <hi>Service</hi> of his <hi>Prince.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the <hi>Commonwealths-men</hi> (for whom the <hi>Libeller</hi> is <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate</hi>) are disturb'd the <hi>King</hi> hath any <hi>Army</hi> at all. Yet had their beloved <hi>Monmouth</hi> prevail'd, (that <hi>Protestont Prince!</hi>) they'd never grudg'd him an <hi>Army,</hi> any more, than their precious <hi>Predecessors</hi> did <hi>Oliver Cromwel;</hi> whose <hi>Title</hi> to the Government was <hi>Equal</hi> to his; but not one jot better. But saith the <hi>Libeller,</hi>—
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The</hi> Sun <hi>will</hi> rise, <hi>the</hi> Actors <hi>fill the</hi> Stage;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And</hi> One and Twenty Months <hi>is not an</hi> Age.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And to strengthen this his <hi>Trayterous Meeter,</hi> he tells us in <hi>Prose,</hi> p. 6.—<q>
                     <hi>England</hi> shall yet make a further advance; 'tis yet more than three months to the Harvest; and at the appointed time shall thy deliverance come; even at the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152706:23"/> time when the <hi>Sun</hi> makes his second Visit to the <hi>Scorpion:</hi> and then will the <hi>Spanish</hi> Apple be grateful to the <hi>English</hi> palate.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Here's <hi>Encouragement</hi> to purpose for <hi>Traytors</hi> and <hi>Rebels;</hi> in case they have but <hi>Faith</hi> strong enough to Credit the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beller.</hi>— The <hi>Sun</hi> will <hi>Rise!</hi> yes, I hope it will, to <hi>discover</hi> such <hi>Sycophants</hi> as you, and <hi>Reward you</hi> too, for your <hi>Blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy</hi> and <hi>Treasons</hi> against <hi>God</hi> and your <hi>Sovereign.— Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> shall yet make a further <hi>advance!</hi> God grant it may, in <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Grandeur.</hi> But God forbid it should, in the <hi>Libellers</hi> Sense: <hi>He</hi> intending nothing thereby, but <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Ruine.</hi> But <hi>Deliverance</hi> shall come at the appointed time! when the <hi>Sun</hi> makes his <hi>second Visit</hi> to the <hi>Scorpion,</hi> and then, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here's <hi>Encouragement</hi> for <hi>Trayt rs</hi> and <hi>Rebels,</hi> I say, with a <hi>witness!</hi> had the <hi>Libeller</hi> call'd all the Infernal <hi>Fiends</hi> to his assistance, he could not have <hi>spoke</hi> more <hi>plainly</hi> or <hi>wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly:</hi> But the best on't is, he hath deluded his <hi>Party</hi> hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to with his <hi>Spurious Oracles</hi> drawn from the <hi>Vernal Ingress,</hi> as you have heard; They have therefore <hi>little Reason</hi> to believe him in <hi>This,</hi> it being likely to prove as <hi>Errant</hi> a <hi>Falshood</hi> as any of his former ridiculous and groundless <hi>sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gestions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Libeller,</hi> notwithstanding, is here come to the <hi>highest pitch</hi> of his <hi>Treason</hi> and <hi>Daring.</hi> For by these <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llish</hi> passages, he most <hi>Treasonably</hi> and <hi>Falsly</hi> imagines the <hi>Death</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> and hath presumed to set <hi>Bounds</hi> to His <hi>Sacred life. [One and Twenty months is not an age!]</hi> For which I doubt not but <hi>Justice</hi> will Requite him. The 25th. of good K. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> III. is not <hi>Repeal'd.</hi> Take notice <hi>Libeller!</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that <hi>Kings</hi> are <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>Vicegerent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and have <hi>long Arm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And why should not I assume as much <hi>Freedom</hi> to Answer this his <hi>Treasonable Insinuation,</hi> as himself hath taken <hi>Liberty</hi> to <hi>Write</hi> and <hi>Print</hi> it? For <hi>Astrology</hi> cannot own any such <hi>damnable suggestion,</hi> unless his <hi>Majesties Birth</hi> were known, which I am confident it is not either to the <hi>Libeller,</hi> or any other <hi>truly.</hi> Arch-Bishop <hi>Laud</hi> in his <hi>Diary</hi> says, His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty was born on <hi>October</hi> the 14th. 1633. but no more, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152706:24"/> yet that good <hi>Bishop</hi> was an <hi>Astrologer.</hi> Mr. <hi>Whitlock</hi> says His Majesty was <hi>Born, October</hi> 13. And I have seen a <hi>Meddal</hi> made at His Majesties <hi>Sacred Birth,</hi> with <hi>October</hi> the 15. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scrib'd upon it. One of which <hi>Meddals</hi> Mr. <hi>Sandford</hi> also owns to have seen. And if the <hi>Day</hi> of this Illustrious <hi>Birth</hi> be thus uncertain, how much more the <hi>time</hi> of the <hi>Day?</hi> And, the <hi>Libeller</hi> knows that <hi>Astrology</hi> requires the <hi>minute,</hi> if Men would be exact in their <hi>Praedicting</hi> of any thing thereon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending.</p>
               <p>There was a <hi>Scheam,</hi> pretended to be His Majesties <hi>Birth</hi> Figure, publish'd (among other things) in <hi>Anno</hi> 1659. [By <hi>no</hi> Enemy to the <hi>Royal Family,</hi> as the Book shews;) which <hi>Scheam</hi> had <hi>Leo</hi> on the <hi>Horoscope,</hi> and this possibly hath hope to misguide the <hi>Libeller,</hi> and his <hi>two</hi> Fellow Incendiaries be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-mention'd; who greedily taking up the matter upon Trust, (as did the Publisher thereof,) hath occasion'd many to believe His Majesties <hi>Nativity</hi> is publickly known. But that <hi>Figure</hi> is not true, for many <hi>Reasons</hi> I could give. I'll mention <hi>one</hi> for <hi>all.</hi> What Imperial <hi>Geniture</hi> did any <hi>man</hi> ever see, that had the <hi>Moon</hi> in <hi>Duodecima Domo?</hi> That very Argument alone is sufficient to <hi>convince</hi> any understan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Astrologer,</hi> of the <hi>Falseness</hi> of that <hi>Figure.</hi> And for the absolute <hi>true one,</hi> I am morally confident it is not, cannot be known. But, in case it were known exactly, what would the <hi>Libeller</hi> do with it? He'd even make the same Jarring false <hi>Musick</hi> with it, as he hath done with the <hi>French</hi> King's <hi>Geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> which is truly known, and Printed by <hi>Morinus</hi> in <hi>Astro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logia Gallica.</hi> And what's that? Why, the <hi>Libeller</hi> doom'd that Great <hi>Martial</hi> Monarch to <hi>Death</hi> three years since, and yet is that Illustrious Prince alive, and likely to live, to prove <hi>him</hi> a very <hi>Impudent,</hi> but Ignorant <hi>Impostor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But alas! It is the <hi>Eclipse</hi> of the <hi>Sun</hi> in <hi>Scorpio, October</hi> 1688. which the <hi>Libeller</hi> refers to, when he tells us of the <hi>"Suns</hi> making his <hi>second Visit</hi> to the <hi>Scorpion,</hi> &amp;c. at which time his XXI Months reaching from <hi>January</hi> 1687. are <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ompleated,</hi> which he says, are not an <hi>Age.</hi>— But what im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial <hi>Astrologer</hi> would dare to give Judgement upon his <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereigns Geniture</hi> at all, much less at so <hi>Wild</hi> and <hi>Groundless</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:152706:24"/> a rate? Can a <hi>small Eclipse,</hi> &amp;c. prove <hi>Fatal</hi> without other Arguments? What Author teaches him this for <hi>Astrology?</hi> 'Tis the <hi>Libellers</hi> Malice, not his Art, that makes him guilty of this palpable and most <hi>Treasonous Falshood.</hi> And although I ought not, and therefore dare not intermeddle too far with so <hi>Sacred</hi> a <hi>Theam</hi> as is the <hi>Life</hi> or <hi>Death</hi> of my <hi>Sovereign,</hi> otherwise than by my <hi>Prayers;</hi> yet I shall presume to tell the <hi>Libeller,</hi> that 'tis not full <hi>Nineteen Years</hi> since, (<hi>viz.</hi> in <hi>October</hi> 1669.) that the <hi>Sun was Eclips'd in the very same place,</hi> as he will be in <hi>October</hi> 1688. And no Danger atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded His <hi>Sacred Person</hi> upon it. Neither can there now, for ought the <hi>Libeller</hi> can read in the <hi>Stars.</hi> And for his <hi>Spanish Apple,</hi> which He says, will then be grateful to the <hi>English Palate;</hi> he tacitly but most wickedly <hi>menaces</hi> His Majesty with <hi>Poyson.</hi> From the which I doubt not but <hi>God,</hi> and all good Mens <hi>Prayers</hi> will protect His <hi>Sacred Person.</hi> Behold! This <hi>Rancorous Bloody Villain!</hi> nothing can <hi>satiate</hi> his <hi>malice,</hi> but the <hi>life</hi> of his <hi>Sovereign!</hi> and that by a <hi>Death</hi> of his own <hi>appointment,</hi> without ground in <hi>Art.</hi> But <hi>Libeller!</hi> let me tell you, <hi>God</hi> hath <hi>preserved Him</hi> from the <hi>Lyon</hi> and the <hi>Bear;</hi> from the <hi>Associators</hi> and the <hi>Exclusio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners!</hi> from <hi>Perils</hi> by <hi>Land!</hi> and <hi>Dangers</hi> by <hi>Sea!</hi> And I doubt not but he will <hi>Deliver Him</hi> from the malicious, groundless <hi>menaces</hi> of this <hi>Uncircumcis'd Philistine,</hi> too. God Almighty, never <hi>Delivers</hi> any from <hi>Iminent Dangers,</hi> but for <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Stupendious Purposes.</hi> As he preserv'd <hi>Moses</hi> in the Water, to be a Leader to his <hi>People. Joseph</hi> from <hi>Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity,</hi> and attempts upon his <hi>Innocence,</hi> to be the <hi>Supporter</hi> of his <hi>Family,</hi> and <hi>Countrey,</hi> by making him the Chief Man in <hi>Aegypt. David</hi> from variety of Dangers, and being <hi>Hunted</hi> as a <hi>Partridge</hi> upon the Mountains, to be the King of his People <hi>Israel. Cum multis aliis,</hi> &amp;c. And, can we believe, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t <hi>God</hi> hath not a mighty <hi>Work</hi> for His <hi>Sacred Majesty to do,</hi> having preserved Him from as <hi>Imminent Dangers</hi> as ever he did any? Assure thy self, vain <hi>Libeller!</hi> thy <hi>Presages</hi> will never be answered, let thy <hi>Wishes</hi> be never so <hi>Bloody</hi> and <hi>Treasonable.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:152706:25"/>
               <p>But this impudent Fellow, as making himself sure of His Majesties true <hi>Nativity,</hi> confidently ventures, (<hi>page</hi> 3.) to write—<q>Saturn in Opposition to the part of Fortune in His Radix, and that giver of life, will in a few months, <hi>(mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his XXI</hi> months, <hi>no doubt,)</hi> be directed to a malefique Ray of <hi>Saturn,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Monstrous Lyar! As false to thy <hi>Art,</hi> as to thy <hi>Sovereign!</hi> what <hi>Genethliacal Astrologer</hi> ever taught, that the <hi>part of Fortunes</hi> directions to any <hi>Promittor</hi> were Dangerous to <hi>life?</hi> Such a <hi>Direction</hi> (as Astrologers tell us) may presage <hi>loss</hi> and <hi>damage</hi> several ways, according to the Nature of the <hi>Star</hi> that is <hi>Promittor,</hi> and <hi>place</hi> it may happen in: but can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>cut off life Ptolomy</hi> teaches us, in Judging of <hi>Natali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Scheams,</hi> first to consider the <hi>Horoscope, Sun,</hi> and <hi>Moon,</hi> for the <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Being</hi> of a <hi>Person</hi> or <hi>City,</hi> &amp;c. and next to take care of its <hi>well-being,</hi> and that was by minding the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or place of the <hi>part of Fortune,</hi> which they commonly call'd the <hi>Lunar Horoscope,</hi> because projected from the <hi>Luminaries</hi> and the <hi>Ascendant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This was <hi>Ptolomy</hi>'s method, and yet the Impudent <hi>Libel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> is not asham'd to vouch <hi>Ptolomy</hi> for this his new Discove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. 13. But I have taken the pains to read <hi>Ptolomy</hi> in both those Chapters of his third Book, and, <hi>Truth be my Witness,</hi> there is not one word in either of them that <hi>sounds</hi> any thing like to what he <hi>asserts.</hi> Nor do the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of those Chapters lead him to any such purpose. He therefore hath bely'd <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> and is not to be credited, The first of those Chapters, treats, <hi>De impedimentis &amp; infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatibus Nati accidentibus Corpori.</hi> The second discourses, <hi>De qualitatibus animae Nati.</hi> Certainly, the <hi>Libeller,</hi> the Morning before he wrote this palpable <hi>Untrath,</hi> offer'd Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice at the <hi>Altar</hi> of the Goddess <hi>Laverna,</hi> in some such like Supplication as this,—
<q>
                     <l>— Pulchra <hi>Laverna!</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Da mihi fallere, da justum sanctum{que} videri,</l>
                     <l>Noctum peccatis &amp; fraudibus obj ce Nubem;</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:152706:25"/>
               <p>Thus in <hi>English.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Goddess</hi> most <hi>Fair!</hi> this <hi>Suit</hi> deny me not,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>k</hi> and <hi>Lye</hi> I may, and yet be <hi>thought</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>An <hi>Arrist Just:</hi> my Knavish <hi>Frauds</hi> o'respread,</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Sable-Clouds,</hi> that they may <hi>ne're</hi> be <hi>Read.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>But, what if <hi>Ptolomy</hi> had said so, which you see he doth not. What stead would it have stood him in? unless the exact <hi>Horoscope</hi> of that <hi>Royal Birth</hi> were known. And that it must be before the place of the <hi>Part of Fortune</hi> can be obtain'd. Thus this busie Man endeavours to <hi>Flie</hi> without <hi>Wings,</hi> and vainly labours to exalt himself (with the Lord <hi>Montaign</hi>'s <hi>Turnebus</hi>) as if he understood <hi>all things;</hi> when in <hi>Truth,</hi> he is a very <hi>shallow Fellow</hi> in the Art of <hi>Astrology,</hi> and hath nothing to value himself upon, but his common <hi>Talents</hi> of <hi>Treason, Atheism,</hi> and impudent <hi>Daring.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here, I was about to lay by my Pen; but that I had fresh and better consider'd the <hi>Libeller</hi>'s Gross Prevarications and Abuse of his Art in deriving all his malicious Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from one single (false) <hi>Ingress▪</hi> and a Transit or two, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and neglecting more <hi>weighty Causes,</hi> by which an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tist ought to have been Govern'd in Praedicting of Futuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. As the great Conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> which presides over this present Age; together, with other lesser Causes. The True and Natural <hi>Effects</hi> of which, I shall as briefly as I can run over, and so conclude.</p>
               <p>Let it in the first place be remembred, that the World is under the Regency of the <hi>Fiery Trigon,</hi> and so will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue untill about, or somewhat after, the year 1800, <hi>viz.</hi> For 113 years yet to come. But we, at this time are more particularly subject to the Government of a Conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> in <hi>Leo,</hi> the <hi>Sun</hi>'s Domal Dignity: The Influence whereof will extend unto 1702. yet 15 years to come. At which time will be Celebrated another Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of the same <hi>Planets</hi> in <hi>Aries, (England</hi>'s Horoscope) the first Sign of the <hi>Zodiack,</hi> continuing the same <hi>Trigon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, we will briefly enquire into the <hi>Effects</hi> of this Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Synod.</hi> Authors tell us, that,— <hi>Sub Arietis Triangulo
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152706:26"/> sunt Monarchiae ingentes,</hi> &amp;c.— When such a Conjunction happens in <hi>Aries,</hi> there will be an appearance of <hi>Mighty Monarchs,</hi> and that Just and Pious Laws shall be Enacted for the Preservation of Men; and People will be more inclin'd to Piety and Devotion than formerly, and be more strict and serious in their Enquiries after things <hi>Divine,</hi> or belonging to a <hi>Future Life;</hi> They will abandon Sensuality, Fraud, Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrisy, and each thing that leads to Destruction: and be more Just and Virtuous in their actions towards God, and one another.</p>
               <p>Further,— <hi>Dum fiunt Magnae Conjunctionis in Trigono primo, quae durant annis</hi> 199, <hi>&amp; singulis</hi> 20. <hi>fiunt annis,</hi> &amp;c. During the time of the great Conjunctions of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> in the first Triplicity, which continues 199 years from their first entring the same; and are therein once every 20 years repeated: (saith <hi>Campanello</hi>) there arises in the World, New <hi>Empires, Monarchies,</hi> and with them much Peace and Tranquility, by reason of the Power the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> have in that <hi>Trigon.</hi>— And the Learned <hi>Dasipodius</hi> fortifies the said Opinion, thus,— <hi>Conjunctones in signis igneis, si fiant,</hi> &amp;c.— If Conjunctions of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour <hi>Planets</hi> happen to be made in the <hi>Fiery Triplicity,</hi> New <hi>Empires</hi> and <hi>Monarchy's</hi> are erected in the World, for as much as the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> bear sway therein; and there will also be an Apparition of <hi>Wise</hi> and <hi>Learned</hi> Persons; and much Peace and Tranquility will be visible among Men, <hi>&amp;c. Dasip. Aph.</hi> 64.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Sun</hi> Naturally signifies Empire and Glory; and <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi> promotes Goodness, Wisdom, Virtue, and Piety; which evermore preserves Empires; as the contrary Vices most certainly brings them to Destruction. And this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider'd, it must be of excellent consequence to the World, (so much thereof at least as is therein concern'd) when such Conjunctions are Influencing of it.</p>
               <p>Give me leave to search a little into the <hi>Effects▪</hi> which have formerly attended some of those Noble Conjunctions, and thence demonstrate the Truth of these <hi>Aphorisms.</hi> I will be very brief.— It was under the Influence of such a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152706:26"/> Conjunction that the <hi>Assyrian</hi> Monarchy began; and that <hi>Nabonasser</hi> advanc'd to the Monarchy of the <hi>Babylonians,</hi> giving them a New <hi>Aera.</hi> Under such a Conjunction, <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan</hi> says, the first <hi>Emperour</hi> appear'd. 'Twas under this <hi>Trigon,</hi> that the most Famous of Men have appear'd in the World, <hi>viz. Moses, Aaron, Joshua, Hezekiah; David, Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> &amp;c. so also <hi>Thales,</hi> and all the rest of the <hi>Seven Sages</hi> under this <hi>Trigon,</hi> saith the Learned Mr. <hi>John Butler,</hi> (in a Manuscript of all the Conjunctions of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> which he kindly gave to me,) <hi>Joseph</hi> was born, and all the XII. <hi>Patriarchs.</hi> And that <hi>Osiris</hi> began his Famous March over all <hi>Asia,</hi> teaching them to sow <hi>Corn,</hi> Plant <hi>Vines,</hi> make <hi>Wine,</hi> &amp;c. The Holy <hi>David</hi> was advanc'd (through many difficulties) to be King of <hi>Israel.</hi> The <hi>Olympick Games,</hi> Famous for above 1000. years after, (he saith) began under this <hi>Trigon.</hi> And also, that under the same, <hi>Sylla</hi> arose, and became the first Imperial Monarch of <hi>Rome.</hi> The <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans were</hi> taught <hi>Physick, Agriculture, Grinding, Forging, Brewing,</hi> &amp;c. under this <hi>Triangle.</hi> And under the same, many Famous Cities have been built, as <hi>Memphis,</hi> (now Grand <hi>Cairo</hi>) in <hi>Aegypt:</hi> But whether by <hi>Apis</hi> or <hi>Epaphos,</hi> I will not dispute. <hi>Sparta, Lacaedemon, Syracuse, Tarentum, Rhegium, Abdera, cum multis aliis,</hi> all Erected under this <hi>Trigon.</hi> So likewise the Famous Universities of <hi>Oxford, Cambridge, Tholouse</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> &amp;c.— But, to instance in One for All, let us (in Duty and Thankfulness to <hi>God</hi>) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that, according to his good pleasure, (for the Enno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of this Famous <hi>Trigon</hi>) the Blessed <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Saviour</hi> of the World was born of a <hi>Virgin,</hi> (under the same,) and became <hi>Incarnate,</hi> to take away the sins of the World, and reconciled Lapsed <hi>Mankind</hi> to a greatly offended <hi>Deity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By this short account, we may reasonably Judge of the <hi>Effects</hi> Dependant on the present Famous Conjunction; which must, according to the Course of Nature, be of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable advantage unto the World, and those particular <hi>Kingdoms, Cities,</hi> &amp;c. that are subjected to this <hi>Ignean Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity,</hi> under a Friendly Consideration. 'Tis the <hi>Fire</hi> that Purifies all things. And this Conjunctions Influences (<hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:152706:27"/> bearing rule herein) will most happily consume all the <hi>Dross</hi> and <hi>Dregs</hi> of <hi>Fanaticism, Fraud,</hi> and <hi>Hipocrisy,</hi> (which hath so long infatuated the World,) and leave us only the Pure Gold of <hi>Peace, Felicity, Religion, Honour,</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,</hi> &amp;c, And, what if I should say, they will salute us with Durable new <hi>Monarchies,</hi> New <hi>Cities,</hi> New <hi>Arts,</hi> &amp;c. The Conjunction is Fixed, and Fixed Signs relate to things of duration, and continuance.— Mistake me not. I do not mean that the <hi>Effects</hi> of this Famous Conjunction shall be of so <hi>all-Glorious</hi> an Influence, or shall so far signifie <hi>Peace, Piety, Honour, Quiet,</hi> and <hi>Content;</hi> as that all War, Discontent, Atheism, or Dishonour should wholly <hi>cease,</hi> or be <hi>absent.</hi> No! What year was there ever so <hi>Dry,</hi> but that it admitted of some <hi>moisture?</hi> Or so <hi>Prosperous,</hi> but that some Men met <hi>Infelicity</hi> therein? The <hi>Antipathies</hi> of Nature can no more be destroy'd, than the <hi>Sympathies.</hi> Both, may be <hi>intended</hi> or <hi>remitted,</hi> but not (while the World lasts) <hi>abolished.</hi> A Man be said to be a good Man, and yet guilty of some Immortalities. And a Year may be said to be a <hi>moist,</hi> or a <hi>dry</hi> One, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in <hi>comparison</hi> of the <hi>moisture,</hi> or <hi>drought</hi> it is laden with. All the Diversity or Variety that appears in the World, is so but by <hi>comparison,</hi> viz. In respect of a <hi>Dry</hi> Year, or of a <hi>Temperate,</hi> such a Year may be reputed <hi>moist.</hi> Or, in regard of a <hi>Fruitful</hi> Revolution; such a one may be term'd <hi>Barren.</hi> But there can be no Year in which all <hi>Four Qualities</hi> shall not be Apparent and Visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. And thus ought we to understand the significations of the <hi>Stars</hi> at large, and of this Famous. <hi>Ignean</hi> Conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> in particular; and not otherwise. For while there is a <hi>Horoscope,</hi> and Point <hi>Culminant,</hi> there will be a <hi>Seventh,</hi> and a <hi>Twelfth</hi> Angle, <hi>i. e.</hi> As long as there are <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Actions</hi> in the World, so long there will be <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> and <hi>Opposition</hi> to them. As there are Persons and Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with whom this Great Conjunction accords, so there are such with whom its Influences Antipathize. The ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of an Amicable Configuration is chiefly this, that, like the <hi>Diurnal</hi> Arch in Summer, we have <hi>(plus Solis)</hi> more of <hi>Good</hi> than of <hi>Evil;</hi> and that the <hi>Evil</hi> it self is
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152706:27"/> kept under, from being able to do the World any material or signal Damage.</p>
               <p>But the <hi>Libeller,</hi> (or some like him) may interrogate, what though Great and Famous <hi>Persons,</hi> and <hi>Actions</hi> have been the <hi>Effects</hi> of these Notable <hi>Congresses</hi> formerly? and perhaps may again now also appear during the continuance of this <hi>Trigon?</hi> Why should they be more visible to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> or <hi>Rome,</hi> than to any other Kingdoms, Cities, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Or, why at this time more than another? I answer.— That the Effects of this Conjunction cannot concern <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>England,</hi> more, than they will other <hi>places</hi> which are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually related to that <hi>Triplicity.</hi> To such they will be of a suitable signification. But they will much more relate to those Famous Places, than to others that are either not at all, or else not <hi>Equally</hi> concern'd with them. Every <hi>Countrey, Kingdom,</hi> or <hi>City,</hi> &amp;c. is not in <hi>Trine</hi> to the <hi>Conjunction,</hi> or in good Configuration with it, therefore cannot be equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly advantaged thereby. Some Kingdoms, Provinces, Cities, Societies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are in <hi>Quadrate,</hi> or <hi>Opposition</hi> to this Noble <hi>Congress:</hi> Others have <hi>Horoscopes,</hi> and <hi>Hylegiacal</hi> Points not at all beholding it. To such therefore it will be either of an Opposite, or of no signification at all.</p>
               <p>But all <hi>Astrologers</hi> concur, that those Places and Persons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that <hi>Harmonise</hi> with the Conjunction, will be sharers in its Nobler Influences; and those that are <hi>Discordant</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, will partake of its most adverse and contrary Effects. Now <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>England</hi> being related to this Conjunction very peculiarly, (though not Exclusive of all other Places) are the more certain Eminently to share in its Effects, and that as I said for good.</p>
               <p>That <hi>England</hi> is subject to the <hi>Fiery Trigon,</hi> is, with Astrologers out of Dispute. <hi>Ptolemy</hi> himself places it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Aries,</hi> and <hi>Mars; Unde impatientes regni,</hi> &amp;c. saith He; And that truly enough, it being of the Nature of Collerick Countries, as well as Persons, to <hi>Aspire, Tyranize,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>Cardanus</hi> adds, that therefore we are a Rebellious and Unlucky People: And that also, is not to be disallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of, when labouring under Rebellious and Tyrannous Influences.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:152706:28"/>
                  <l>The Warlike <hi>Ram</hi> Ascends in <hi>England<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Scheam,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Mars,</hi> or <hi>Mars</hi> his Sons, must Govern them.</l>
               </q>
               <p>For we must know it for a Truth, that all the shining Diamonds of Heaven do not emit such Salutiferous and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serving <hi>Rayes</hi> as doth the Planet <hi>Jupiter:</hi> Neither is <hi>Jupiter</hi> always the Ruler of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Conjunction;</hi> (though here he be) sometimes it happens that he is a <hi>Patient</hi> or Sufferer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self; and Envious <hi>Saturn</hi> will bear the Rule over him But now (Blessed be God) it is otherwise.</p>
               <p>Now, to strengthen the Opinion (though it scarce need) that <hi>Aries</hi> is the <hi>Horoscope</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> I have seen a <hi>Figure</hi> of Heaven, said to be that of <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Conquerors</hi> first Landing in <hi>England;</hi> and it is this, and probably the true time thereof, or very near: as I shall upon another occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on endeavour elsewhere to Demonstrate.</p>
               <figure>
                  <p>The Figure of <hi>HEA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VEN</hi> at the time of Duke <hi>WILLIAM,</hi> Sirnamed the <hi>Conqueror,</hi> his Entrance into <hi>ENGLAND</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>☽ à □ ♂. <hi>ad</hi> △ 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> □ ☉.</p>
                  <figDesc>astrological chart</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:152706:28"/>
               <p>Whether this be the very true Figure of Duke <hi>William</hi>'s Landing at <hi>Pemsey</hi> I will not absolutely affirm; but it looks so like the True One, (chiefly as it accords to the Kingdoms Original <hi>Horoscope</hi>) that it may, <hi>cum graro Salis,</hi> be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted for the truth. A <hi>Cardinal</hi> Scheme agrees well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to a vigorous, Active People; and <hi>Mars</hi> Lord of the Ascendant in <hi>Trine</hi> to it, and in Conjunction with a Star of his own Nature, in Sextile of the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> &amp;c. well signifies a Disposition to Liberty, Pleasure, War, Victory, Conquest of Enemies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with other matters visible in the Figure, which I purposely pass over; All confirming it to be nearly true. And if so, let us consider how the <hi>Full Moon</hi> Scheme before the Great Conjunction in 1682. agrees herewith. In that Figure the <hi>Laminaries</hi> are in a Friendly Aspect to the Place of the <hi>Conjunction;</hi> And as the <hi>Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> it self fell in <hi>Trine</hi> to the Ascendent of <hi>England,</hi> so it was Celebrated near the place of <hi>Jupiter</hi> in this <hi>Scheme,</hi> and in partile Trine of the Ninth Angle (which is termed <hi>Domus Religionis</hi>) which is govern'd by <hi>Jupiter.</hi> All which Arguments prove <hi>England</hi> to be Eminently concern'd in the Effects of this Conjunction, and that for Good. And that which makes it the more considerable, the <hi>Profectional</hi> Scheme of this <hi>Coel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>stial Synod,</hi> is in <hi>Trine</hi> to that of the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ull Moon</hi> preceding it, and therein return'd to the Place of the Conjunction, and that of <hi>Jupiter</hi> himself in the Radix. I want Room (if it were convenient) to Explain all these Excellent Arguments. — <hi>Unity in Religion</hi> (I say) is the main intendment of this Famous Congress; and those particular Testimonies tell us where? and to whom? <hi>Si Deus &amp; Astra nobiscum, quis contra nos?</hi> Some may expect a Judgement Astrological on this remarkable Figure, (a <hi>Cardinal</hi> one indeed, and semblable to the Actions and Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions of this Warlike Nation) but that is Irrelative to my present Purpose. My business being to shew the Partiality and Neglect of the <hi>Libeller,</hi> or his malice rather, that thus hath dared to Disturb the Peace of his <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Countrey,</hi> (as far as lay in him) under pretence of drawing Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from the <hi>Stars;</hi> whereas had he honestly consider'd them, they had been found wholly against him.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:152706:29"/>
               <p>But further, for as much as the <hi>Libeller</hi> hath Confidently joyned <hi>Rome</hi> with <hi>England</hi> to suffer all the <hi>Plagues</hi> his Envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Pen was able to Scatter; I will here (to manifest his <hi>Folly</hi> as well as <hi>Falseness</hi>) Produce the Nativity of <hi>Rome,</hi> as I find it in <hi>Gauricus;</hi> that the world may see what little Ground he had so basely to bespatter it.</p>
               <figure>
                  <p>The PALLADIUM of ROME, agreeing to its Second Restau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. As it is found in LUCAS GAURICUS.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Latit</hi> ROMAE.</p>
                  <p>☽. <hi>â Vac. ad</hi> ✶ ☉.</p>
                  <figDesc>astrological chart</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>What skilful Astrologer is there, that seriously viewing, this Figure of Heaven, would dare to pronounce <hi>Destruction</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> under a Conjunction in the Fiery <hi>Triangle?</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold how all the Planets are rang'd in Order, all <hi>(Supra ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram</hi> too,) to assist it by their Harmonious Positions. <hi>Pisces Aries, Taurus, Gemini, Cancer,</hi> all possess'd by <hi>Planets.</hi> Fortunate <hi>Stars, Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> in the <hi>medium Coeli;</hi> and the <hi>Sun</hi> in <hi>Aries,</hi> his Exaltation, smiling on the <hi>Horo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scope</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:152706:29"/> with a Trigonal Ray: The <hi>Moon</hi> increasing in the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle of <hi>Hopes</hi> and <hi>Assistance,</hi> applying to the <hi>Sextile</hi> of the <hi>Sun</hi> in the Ninth Angle. An Admirable Position of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> enough to Dazle the Eyes of <hi>Romes</hi> greatest Enemies: and sufficient to confirm them, that they shall be no more able to <hi>prevail</hi> against <hi>Her,</hi> then the <hi>Gates</hi> of <hi>Hell</hi> can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the <hi>Truth She</hi> Maintains. And had that Whimsical Astrologer, who asum'd the Name of <hi>RUTH,</hi> (which Mr. <hi>Maxwel</hi> gives us notice of in his Collection of <hi>Prophesies,</hi> &amp;c.) but truly observed the <hi>Glories</hi> of this Coelestial Scheme, he could never have been so <hi>Rash</hi> or <hi>Fanciful,</hi> as to have Praedicted the <hi>Downfal</hi> of this Famous <hi>City,</hi> and <hi>Hierarchy</hi> as He did, from a Conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> in <hi>Scorpio,</hi> 1484. and by sundry <hi>Pictures,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther frothy fallacious Stories; which vain presage, it hath now survived <hi>(laus Deo)</hi> more then 200. years, so that we see—
<q>
                     <l>Stout <hi>Rome</hi> stands still, a Bulwark, to Defie,</l>
                     <l>The Pen-Granado's of False Phrophesie.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>You see by this, there have been other <hi>Fops</hi> and <hi>Impostors</hi> as well as the <hi>Libeller,</hi> and long before him too, that have been stretching their <hi>Skill,</hi> and straining their <hi>Credits,</hi> to strike at <hi>Rome.</hi> Mr. <hi>Potter</hi> flirted at it from the Number of the Beast, 666. And many others have done the same, by <hi>Chronograms, Crotchets, Prophesies, Dreams,</hi> &amp;c. But alass! how vainly! All of them have been deluded and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serably deceived in their hopes; and, may they not also be justly <hi>derived</hi> too? <hi>Plus faetent stercora mota.</hi> I will rake into this Dirty Puddle no further.</p>
               <p>Let me now consider how matters stand at present with that Noble <hi>Place</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> in respect of Coelestial Causes. And here I find this Famous <hi>Conjunction</hi> to fall in the very <hi>Horoscope</hi> of <hi>Romes Palladium;</hi> and the <hi>Moon</hi> in the <hi>Pleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunium Figure</hi> exactly return'd <hi>ad locum Solis,</hi> and <hi>Sextilum Proprium</hi> therein. And if the <hi>Luminaries</hi> are the grand <hi>Spirits</hi> of the World, and the Life of All things Living, (as
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152706:30"/> saith <hi>Hermes Trismegistus,— Sol &amp; Luna post Deum, Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um viventium vita sunt.</hi>) then their places being fortuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in any Radix, must add to the Life and Vigor, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently, to the Honour and Splendor of that Place unto whom they belong. <hi>Ergo,</hi> much Happiness, and Success must hereby be intended to the <hi>See</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> maugre all the <hi>Libellers</hi> Malicious Predictions to the Contrary; And this Judgement is the Natural Result of <hi>Art.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Further, we may observe, In the <hi>Profectional</hi> Scheme, that the <hi>Conjunction</hi> is returned to the <hi>Fifth</hi> Angle; which (according to Natural Causes) renders that <hi>Holy See</hi> Pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous, and Successful, and Prevailing, hy her <hi>Envoys, Agents</hi> or <hi>Ambassadors,</hi> &amp;c. and heaps Honours and Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages upon many of her <hi>Obedient Children,</hi> and denotes them, also, happy in their Endeavours; and that their Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Praise-worthy <hi>Labours</hi> will be more Easie and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful, and less Hazardous to them, than in some former years; that they shall be respected, and kindly treated where ever they come; and not be (while this Conjunction <hi>Rules</hi>) subject to suffer under the Damnable <hi>Perjuries</hi> of <hi>Satan</hi>'s <hi>Imps,</hi> as lately they most wrongfully did.</p>
               <p>I cannot Enlarge upon these two Illustrious <hi>Genitures;</hi> which if consider'd (as you have heard) with the two other mention'd <hi>Schemes,</hi> together with <hi>Revolutions</hi> and <hi>Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of the <hi>Planets,</hi> &amp;c. (A large, and Laborious task?) do pronounce most <hi>Glorious things,</hi> not only to <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> in particular, but to all <hi>Christendom;</hi> to the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of the <hi>True Religion,</hi> and to the Depression of the <hi>Devils</hi> Kingdom, <hi>Heresy, Schism,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Here, let me premise, that when I mention <hi>Religion,</hi> &amp;c. I do it not as if I believ'd the <hi>Stars</hi> acted <hi>Fatally</hi> upon <hi>Men,</hi> or that they had any Dominion over <hi>Consciences,</hi> or matters truly <hi>Divine.</hi> I am satisfi'd (with <hi>Indagines</hi>) that they <hi>Incline</hi> only, and that (many times) very <hi>gently</hi> too; the <hi>Mind</hi> is affected with Stellary <hi>Influences,</hi> only by the media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Organs,</hi> and not Directly. And the <hi>Soul</hi> is a free Agent. 'Tis the <hi>Mutable</hi> part of <hi>Religion</hi> only, that is <hi>Cognoscible</hi> to the <hi>Stars;</hi> that part of it which is Subject
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:152706:30"/> to our <hi>Senses:</hi> But the <hi>Substance,</hi> or <hi>Essence</hi> thereof is above their <hi>Influences,</hi> and, as being <hi>Eternal,</hi> admits of neither <hi>Alteration</hi> or <hi>Addition.</hi> Wherefore the <hi>Stars</hi> may discover a <hi>Hipocrite</hi> or <hi>Heretick,</hi> &amp;c. because such are led by their <hi>sensual</hi> Appetites, and not by the Spirit of <hi>Unity.</hi> But alas! they can never Declare a <hi>Christian.</hi> A True <hi>christian</hi> is the Holy Apostles Spiritual Man, that <hi>Judgeth</hi> all things, and is Judged of None: He is Influenced by a <hi>Heaven</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the <hi>Stars;</hi> Even the <hi>Caelum Empyreum,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This premis'd, I say then with <hi>Origanus,</hi> &amp;c. that the <hi>Christian</hi> Religion <hi>(secundum formam)</hi> is under the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> whence <hi>Cardan</hi> says — <hi>Lex Christiana, Lex est Pietatis, Justitiae, Fidei, Simplicitatis,</hi> &amp;c. That the Christian Law, is a Law of Piety, Justice, Integrity, Faith, Simplicity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> — All which <hi>Virtues,</hi> as they are own'd by the Good Planet <hi>Jupiter,</hi> will be Improved and Advanced, during the Influence of this <hi>Conjunction,</hi> to the Honour of <hi>God,</hi> and the Happiness of those Gountries, Kingdoms, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that are subject to the Fiery Trigon. <hi>Jupiters</hi> Influences are ever benefique.— <hi>Nam â Jove amicitie, fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dera, religiosi,</hi> &amp;c. when <hi>Jupiter</hi> hath Supreme Rule in a Conjunction, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He intimates many Notable and Serious Enquiries into former Alliances, Leagues, Friendships and matters relating to <hi>Religion,</hi> and to the <hi>Civil Customs</hi> of Kingdoms, Countreys, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to an <hi>Abolishing</hi> of sundry un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>just <hi>Encroachments.</hi> A <hi>Reformation</hi> of many Notorious <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buses;</hi> and to an Extirpation of <hi>Fraud,</hi> and <hi>Injustice.</hi> So far are <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>England</hi> from suffering what the <hi>Libeller</hi> awards, that the Grand Chanel of <hi>Division</hi> and <hi>Confusion</hi> is like to be stop'd up, and turn'd into the Joyful Current of <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Unity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to <hi>England</hi> in particular, give me leave to remember a Notable passage in <hi>Michael Nostradamus,</hi> Written about 130. years since, <hi>viz.</hi> some short time after the pretended <hi>Reformation;</hi> which is thus,
<q>
                     <l>Le grand Empire sera pars L' Angleterre.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A mighty</hi> Empire England <hi>Once shall be.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:152706:31"/> And, allowing it a <hi>Prophesy,</hi> it hath not been yet fulfill'd. Neither can it be more likely to meet an accomplishment then in this present Age: <hi>England</hi> being now Govern'd by a <hi>Warlike-Martial Prince,</hi> and under the Influence of a Noble <hi>Regal</hi> Conjunction.</p>
               <p>Again, It is an allow'd <hi>Axiom</hi> among <hi>Astrologers,— Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivitates quae configurantur cum propinquis figuris duorum superiorum Conjunctionem,</hi> &amp;c.— That those Provinces, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, Cities and Persons, whose Genitures correspond with the Figure of the last Ruling Conjunction of the Superiours, will remarkably advance in Honour and Grandeur, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and shall perform some more than ordinary Action or Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons worthy the same. The <hi>Genesis</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> (as you have seen) doth happily agree with that of the present Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Famous Conjunction. It follows therefore clearly (<hi>non obstante,</hi> the <hi>Libellers</hi> Rabsheka-Railing) that <hi>Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> will advance and prosper Eminently under the Influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this <hi>Regal Conjunction;</hi> and that as well in things <hi>Sacred</hi> as <hi>Secular;</hi> to the rejoycing of the <hi>Truly Loyal,</hi> and Consternation of its <hi>Enemies.</hi> I may therefore be held to affirm,— <q>That whoever <hi>He,</hi> or <hi>They</hi> be, that shall presume to promise themselves any Encouragement or Security in their <hi>Practices</hi> or <hi>Conspiracies</hi> against the Illustrious <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch</hi> of these Nations, or the Peaceable <hi>Government</hi> thereof, <hi>They</hi> will be most miserably <hi>deluded</hi> and <hi>decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved;</hi> and be <hi>Frustrate</hi> in all their designs, by a timely dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery thereof: Let <hi>Him,</hi> or <hi>Them,</hi> Act never so <hi>Crafti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> or <hi>Occultly;</hi> and they will come to be expos'd to the greatest and severest of <hi>punishments</hi> as their <hi>Treasons</hi> can deserve, or the <hi>Law</hi> can inflict; even to the Destruction of their <hi>Persons,</hi> Ruine of their <hi>Estates;</hi> and possibly to the utter Extirpation of their <hi>Names</hi> and <hi>Families.</hi>
                  </q>— Let them remember the sad, but just <hi>Destinie</hi> which of late be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell their <hi>Brethren,</hi> and Fellow Conspirators in the <hi>West,</hi> viz. <hi>Anno</hi> 1685.</p>
               <p>Moreover, if the <hi>Evil</hi> Figures of a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> or <hi>City,</hi> &amp;c. (as says the Famous <hi>Ptolemy</hi>) are intended, or remitted ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>contrary</hi> Configurations of the Heavens, or
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:152706:31"/> Stars; Then our present Argument receives still greater strength. For, it is most apparent, that the Malignant and Angry Aspects of the Stars are removed from us. The late general troubled, and (I was about to say) unparallel'd <hi>Fate</hi> which fo furiously afflicted us, was occasion'd by the great Equinoctial <hi>Opposition</hi> of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter;</hi> preceding it, Which, as aggravated by other lesser Causes, made it so. <hi>Violent, Fierce, Turbulent,</hi> and <hi>Raging.</hi> It happen'd from <hi>Aries</hi> and <hi>Libra;</hi> and generated Diseases and Disturbances in the <hi>Head.</hi> (As well of Kingdoms, and Cities, as Persons) Which was wittily noted by the Author of the MEDAL, speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the (then) <hi>Achitophel</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> telling Him,—
<q>That, the <hi>Pox'd Nation</hi> felt him in their <hi>Brains.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Whence Issued so many Damnable, Wicked and unheard of <hi>Plots</hi> and <hi>Conspiracies</hi> of the <hi>Vulgar</hi> and <hi>Baser</hi> sort, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their <hi>Superiours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now, I say, be it known unto all the World, that those Malignant <hi>Dog-Stars,</hi> under whose fierce Influences we were of late so horribly <hi>worry'd,</hi> are wholly <hi>remitted,</hi> being super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded by those of a more Noble, Generous, Temprate, Fixed and Preserving Influence, <hi>viz.</hi> that of the fore-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> in <hi>Leo.</hi> No more <hi>Wallers,</hi> now, to be heard of, to look for <hi>Priests</hi> in <hi>Pepper-Boxes;</hi> Or to mistake <hi>Jacobus,</hi> s, for <hi>Popish Images;</hi> or Rich <hi>Bracelets,</hi> or <hi>Necklaces,</hi> for BEADS; Gold <hi>Watches,</hi> or valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>Jewels,</hi> for <hi>Trinkets</hi> belonging to the <hi>Whore</hi> of <hi>Babilon,</hi> &amp;c. No more <hi>burning</hi> of our Savours <hi>Picture,</hi> to promote <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi> No more of these noon-day <hi>Cheats</hi> now! which were lately perform'd in the Face of the Sun, <hi>in Nomine Dei.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The time of the devouring KITES intimated by <hi>Merlin,</hi> is past. We had them with us in the late <hi>Plot</hi> with a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness! Such a <hi>Perjur'd</hi> Crew of Atheistical and Plundring <hi>Caitiffs</hi> the World was scarce ever acquainted with since <hi>Cain</hi> slew his Innocent Brother. A parcel of Dignify'd <hi>Knaves</hi> too! from <hi>Heraldry</hi> of their own making, <hi>viz</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Otes!</hi> Capt. <hi>Bedlo!</hi> Capt. <hi>Dangerfield!</hi> Esq; <hi>Dugdale!</hi> Mr. <hi>Prance cum multis aliis,</hi> &amp;c.— When as but a short time before, <hi>Otes</hi> beg'd for Six Pence of <hi>Pickering. Bedloe</hi> was
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:152706:32"/> fed out of the <hi>Alms-Basket. Dangerfield</hi> fetch'd out of <hi>Newgate</hi> by a kind-hearted Old Woman; and had been of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>Whipp'd</hi> and <hi>Pillory'd</hi> before for his precious <hi>Pranks. Dugdale</hi> had squander'd away his Lords Money to whom he was <hi>Bayliff;</hi> and to even accounts with his Lordship, swore him into the <hi>Plot.</hi>— Yet, such was the <hi>Iniquity</hi> of the (then) times, these devouring <hi>Varlets</hi> were believ'd, and so strongly <hi>back'd,</hi> and held up by the <hi>Chin,</hi> that every honest <hi>Loyal Man,</hi> and some Great <hi>Noble Men</hi> too, (for these <hi>Birds</hi> of <hi>Prey</hi> slew at all!) which one would have thought had been out of the reach of such Verminous <hi>VVretches;</hi> stood in fear of them, and were <hi>terrify'd</hi> with the danger and noise of their horrid <hi>Mouth-Granodoes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Surely, <hi>Ambrose Merlyn</hi> himself, had he then been alive, would have sworn that these things had been an absolute full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of his Prophecy.— <hi>Et erit tempus Milvorum.</hi> And there shall be a time of <hi>Kites,</hi> &amp;c.— But blessed be God, this <hi>time of Kites</hi> is past. And all the pestiferous and <hi>Perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious</hi> Vermin are either dissipated, or dead, (the <hi>Doctor</hi> only remaining in <hi>Salva Custodia,</hi> to assure us <hi>five</hi> times every <hi>year,</hi> that there was such a time of <hi>Kites</hi> among us.) And every Loyal Man begins to be reduc'd to his right mind again, and to enjoy himself. And so I question not but we shall continue, many and many years, notwithstanding the <hi>Machinations</hi> of Rebellious and Blood-thirsty Men.</p>
               <p>Now, as to what the <hi>Libeller</hi> talks of to attend us from the <hi>Opposition</hi> of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> to come in 1692. and 1693. I say▪ it is not only besides his present <hi>Text</hi> (for he wholly omitted to explain their <hi>Conjunction,</hi> that, being against his Knavish designs) which was a Judgement on the <hi>year</hi> 1687. but a direct and palpable <hi>Contradiction</hi> to what he hath writ. For he has as you have heard (tho' most Falsly) terminated the present happiness and Government of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> by <hi>October</hi> 1688 at the farthest. When the <hi>Sun makes his second visit to the Scorpion,</hi> then the <hi>Spanish Apple,</hi> &amp;c
<q>—And <hi>One</hi> and <hi>Twenty months</hi> is not an <hi>Age.</hi>
                  </q> Which agrees to the foresaid Month of <hi>October.</hi> And yet (forgetting himself) he foolishly tells us of matters to hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:152706:32"/> several years after we all are to be Destroy'd. — <hi>Oportet mendacem esse memorem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But alass! Were there any thing in what he pretends, the <hi>Effects</hi> of an <hi>Opposition,</hi> are ever <hi>Obedient</hi> to those of a <hi>Conjunction.</hi> And if the Congress be <hi>Balsamique,</hi> the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ametrial Ray can never be <hi>Corrosive.</hi> It may indeed <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuerè,</hi> somewhat abate of the Synod's good significations, but can never oppose or alter them.</p>
               <p>Shall I give this <hi>Libeller</hi> a little more Light into the Truth hereof; and that by an Instance or two within our own memories also? Let it then be remembred that there was a <hi>Conjunstion</hi> of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> in <hi>Pisces, February,</hi> 1643. an Irregular Conjunction, and attended with as Anomalous Actions and Effects, <hi>viz.</hi> A <hi>Horrid Rebellion,</hi> and the <hi>Murther</hi> of the Best of <hi>Kings</hi> at his own Door, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I meddle not with any Forrein Effects thereof, though they also were Monstrous and Strange. — The <hi>Opposition</hi> of the same <hi>Planets</hi> happen'd <hi>Anno</hi> 1653. in the Signs <hi>Leo</hi> and <hi>Aquary.</hi> But, what then? Did that mend the matter? or did it not make it worse, rather? 'Tis true, the <hi>Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Rump Parliament</hi> was soon after <hi>Routed.</hi> But, to continue the <hi>Rebellious</hi> Effects of that <hi>Conjunction, Cromwel,</hi> the <hi>Usurper,</hi> was exalted in their Room. Who, with his <hi>Major-Generals,</hi> and Lords of his own making, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Built upon the same wicked and <hi>Perjurious Foundation.</hi> Consult the History of those times, and then tell me, whether the <hi>Opposition</hi> did not answer to the <hi>Conjunction</hi> in it's <hi>Tyranous</hi> and <hi>Rebellious Effects,</hi> as in a Glass, <hi>Face</hi> answers <hi>Face.</hi> Under the Influence of the <hi>Conjunction,</hi> the <hi>Rebells Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd</hi> the <hi>King;</hi> and during the Regency of the <hi>Opposition,</hi> they <hi>Abjur'd</hi> the whole <hi>Royal Line.</hi> Study now, <hi>Libeller,</hi> and then tell me, where's the Difference? They, <hi>viz. Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel,</hi> and his <hi>Party,</hi> could not <hi>Kill</hi> him whom they had <hi>Murther'd</hi> before. But did they not endeavour to <hi>Murther</hi> him in his <hi>Issue?</hi> where now, I say, lyes the <hi>difference</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a <hi>Conjunction</hi> and <hi>Opposition?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take another Instance nearer hand, which perhaps may be more readily remembred, <hi>viz.</hi> the great <hi>Conjunction</hi> of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:152706:33"/>
                  <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> Celebrated in <hi>Sagitary, October</hi> 1663 <hi>Sagitary</hi> is held less <hi>Noble,</hi> and more <hi>Feral,</hi> than <hi>Leo.</hi> This <hi>Conjunction</hi> was succeeded with a very great <hi>Plague,</hi> and terrible <hi>Conflagration</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> &amp;c. Two or three <hi>Wars</hi> with <hi>Holland;</hi> and but a Wavering and Uneasie Peace at home. — Now, the <hi>Opposition</hi> of the said Planets fell in <hi>Aries</hi> and <hi>Libra,</hi> in the Month of <hi>April,</hi> 1673. The very year of the <hi>Discriminating Act,</hi> and of the Earl of <hi>Shafts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi>'s contriving the <hi>TEST,</hi> which was attended with the Damnable <hi>Projects</hi> for an <hi>Association,</hi> and an <hi>Exclusion</hi> of the Lawful <hi>Heir</hi> from his <hi>Birth-right.</hi> And for their more easy compassing thereof, the late Damnable <hi>Plot,</hi> common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call'd <hi>Oates</hi>'s <hi>Plot,</hi> was Spawn'd. The Nation was survey'd by the command of Subjects; who had nothing to do there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and it was also divided into <hi>WORTHY MEN,</hi> and <hi>MEN WORTHY,</hi> by those whose honest business was <hi>Obedience.</hi> His <hi>Majesty</hi> that then Reign'd, was bearded by his <hi>Vassals,</hi> and almost brought into a <hi>Plot</hi> against him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self. Many worthy Persons Innocently suffer'd <hi>Death,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sworn out of their Lives by <hi>Varlets;</hi> and to compleat the Miseries <hi>England</hi> then Lahour'd under. A Noble and Loyal <hi>Lord</hi> was also Sworn out of his Life, and <hi>Dyed</hi> as an Enemy to the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Government.</hi> — Thus thou seest (vain <hi>Libeller</hi>) that the effects of an <hi>Opposition</hi> are ever E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quivalent to those of the <hi>Conjunction</hi> preceding. Can any believe that the <hi>Plague,</hi> and Dreadful <hi>Fire,</hi> which the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction</hi> brought, could be more Mischievous to <hi>England,</hi> then these Damnable <hi>Effects</hi> which follow'd the <hi>Opposition?</hi> This Nation hath Reason to esteem the <hi>Latter</hi> to be the far greater <hi>Plague</hi> of the two; It being far better to fall into the Hands of <hi>God,</hi> then of <hi>Men.</hi> And, therefore the <hi>Mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Menaces</hi> of the <hi>Libeller,</hi> from the <hi>Opposition</hi> of those two Planets, which will happen in 1692. and 1693. are both <hi>vain</hi> and <hi>false,</hi> since the Effects thence to Ensue, muct naturally bear a resemblance to those of the <hi>Conjunction.</hi> And were it not so, the Law of <hi>Nature,</hi> and of the <hi>Stars</hi> (which is all one) were not <hi>Uniform,</hi> as we know it ever is, when not contradicted by <hi>Miracles.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:152706:33"/>
               <p>I should now take notice of his confidence in presuming to <hi>advise</hi> the <hi>German Emperour</hi> to leave the PAGAN, and lead his Forces against the CHRISTIAN TURK; thereby meaning the Great <hi>French King,</hi> and of his still threatning that Illustrious <hi>Monarch</hi> (whom three years since he had im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently pretended to <hi>Kill</hi> by his no-<hi>Art,</hi>) with a three years mischief at his <hi>Doors.</hi> Of his Scandalously twitting <hi>Denmark</hi> with the <hi>weakness</hi> of a STAGGERING PRINCE. Of his Egregions <hi>Flatteries</hi> to the <hi>States</hi> of <hi>Holland.</hi>— That they <hi>shall plow the Ocean with success,</hi> &amp;c.— I should, I fay, have taken notice of all these, and other Villanous Lying passages,— As, who it is this <hi>Varlet</hi> means by his HATED MONARCH, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But having been taught by the Noble <hi>Plutarch,</hi> to keep within my own Sphere, and to ABSTAIN FROM BEANS, <hi>i. e.</hi> Not to concern my self too nearly with the Actions or Affairs of <hi>Princes, Monarchs, States,</hi> &amp;c. I shall leave such matters to be consider'd of by the several Honourable <hi>Agents</hi> or <hi>Ambassadours</hi> of such <hi>Princes</hi> or <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publicks,</hi> unto whom it properly belongs; for them to take <hi>Care</hi> in the places where they reside, that the Honour and Dignity of the <hi>Sovereigns</hi> they Represent; be not Lessen'd, Undervalu'd, or Wounded by <hi>Scandals</hi> in any sort or man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; but much more, when they shall be dishonour'd and Scandaliz'd by Libellous <hi>Prints,</hi> which <hi>proclaims</hi> the same, not only to the <hi>present,</hi> but to <hi>future</hi> Ages for ever.</p>
               <p>And, so I have done with the <hi>Libeller,</hi> for this time pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>God</hi> in mercy to reveal his <hi>Eyes,</hi> and awaken his hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Conscience</hi> to a <hi>love</hi> of the <hi>Truth,</hi> and of true <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Loyalty</hi> toward his Lawful <hi>Sovereign,</hi> whom he hath, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Cause, most maliciously and daringly <hi>provoked.</hi> And also to give him Grace to <hi>Repent</hi> of all his <hi>Atheism, Treason</hi> and <hi>Blasphemy,</hi> intersper'd throughout his wicked <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> and that he may before it be <hi>too late,</hi> crave <hi>Pardon</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and of his Sacred <hi>Majesty</hi> for all his wicked and wilful <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences</hi> committed against both.</p>
               <q>Sero Sapit Ingratus.</q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:152706:34"/>
            <head>POSTCRIPT.</head>
            <p>I Have purposely omitted to search into seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral strains of his Doggrel Poetry, as not willing to understand whom he points at: and yet they seem very plain and intelligible. Hear him in one or two of them.— He says, that in his <hi>wanted Commonwealth</hi> —
<q>
                  <l>No <hi>Charters</hi> seiz'd for <hi>Rome</hi> by New-found VVrit,</l>
                  <l>Nor <hi>City-Rights</hi> question'd as they thought fit,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>ROGUES</hi> made <hi>JUDGES</hi> to Determine it.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And,—
<q>
                  <l>No <hi>FIDLING JUSTICE</hi> there perks up his Head,</l>
                  <l>Prefer'd to <hi>Cheat</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> that gave him Bread.</l>
               </q> With sundry other Venomous <hi>Flirts</hi> at several Eminent and <hi>Loyal Persons,</hi> and some of them by <hi>Name,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Graham,</hi> Mr. <hi>Burton,</hi> &amp;c His <hi>Majesties</hi> Solicitors; possibly, for that they might be appointed to <hi>Prosecute</hi> him for his <hi>Treason.</hi> Of which pray take a Copy thereof as it was <hi>Sworn</hi> against him, and Printed in the <hi>Rye-House Conspiracy,</hi> p. 90. of the <hi>Octavo</hi> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression, <hi>viz. — <hi>This</hi>
               </hi> Examinant (<hi>Mr.</hi> W. WEST) further saith, <hi>That Mr.</hi> Goodenough <hi>told him this</hi> Examinant, <hi>That he had spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to one</hi> PARTRIDGE <hi>a</hi> Shooe-maker <hi>and</hi> Almanack-maker <hi>in</hi> Covent-Garden, <hi>to Act in this</hi> ASSASSINATION, <hi>and that the said</hi> PARTRIDGE <hi>offer'd to</hi> Joyn <hi>in it, if it were to be done in</hi> Town, <hi>but was not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:152706:34"/> to</hi> RIDE, <hi>and therefore could not</hi> Joyn <hi>in the</hi> ATTEMPT <hi>out of</hi> London. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther saith, <hi>That the said</hi> PARTRIDGE <hi>had erected some</hi> Scheams, <hi>and thereby found the Duke of</hi> YORK <hi>would scarce out-live</hi> March <hi>or</hi> April: <hi>And that the</hi> KING <hi>was under an</hi> Ill Direction <hi>too, and the</hi> PEOPLE <hi>would be</hi> VICTORIOUS. <hi>And Mr.</hi> Riley <hi>told this</hi> Examinant <hi>the same thing as to the</hi> Scheams <hi>erected by</hi> PARTRIDGE.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Libellers</hi> horrid <hi>Treasons</hi> being thus dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd, he fled into <hi>Holland</hi> to avoid the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment due unto them; and there the more fully to <hi>Evince</hi> his <hi>Guilt,</hi> he excites, (as much as in him lies) by his <hi>Poysonous</hi> Pen to a <hi>Rebellion</hi> against his Lawful <hi>King.</hi> Assuring his <hi>Associa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> Brethren, <hi>The advantage is far greater to the Patrons of Liberty, Courage,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>than to the Patrons of Popery, and that Popery will not stand in</hi> England <hi>many months — but decline, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish; — And then run <hi>Rogues.</hi>
               </hi> Now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare Mr. <hi>West</hi>'s Testimony, and see if it do not exactly jump with the <hi>Libellers Predictions.</hi>— And, yet, behold the <hi>Impudence</hi> of this <hi>Wretch!</hi> after all this <hi>Treason,</hi> and reiterated Provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of His <hi>Majesty,</hi> abusing the Reverend <hi>Judges,</hi> and other his malicious <hi>Scandals,</hi> as you have heard,— He dares with the <hi>Whore</hi> in the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs,</hi> wipe his mouth, and say he hath done no <hi>Evil;</hi> But hath the hard'ned confidence as to send over an <hi>Almanack</hi> to <hi>London,</hi> to be Printed for 1688.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:152706:35"/>
            <p>Finally, If any shall Judge me too <hi>Sharp</hi> in this my <hi>Reply;</hi> I must presume to tell them, that if they justly consider the occasion given, they'l then think me rather too <hi>sparing</hi> in my Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versions upon so <hi>Horrid</hi> a LIBELL; Wherein the <hi>Libeller</hi> hath <hi>Traiterously traduc'd</hi> his <hi>Liege Lord</hi> and <hi>Sovereign,</hi> menac'd His <hi>Royal Life,</hi> and set bounds thereunto, to the Dishonour of the King of Kings, whose Prerogative it is; Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturb'd and <hi>Bespatter'd</hi> his <hi>Native Countrey,</hi> from whence he drew his <hi>Infamous Breath;</hi> Scandaliz'd and threat'ned all the <hi>Reverend Judges</hi> of the Realm, Blasphem'd <hi>Christian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> and the <hi>Clergy</hi> of both Churches; and, to these his Enormous <hi>purposes</hi> hath unworthily prostituted <hi>Astrology,</hi> one of the most <hi>Antient</hi> and <hi>Ʋseful Sciences</hi> in the World, and ever in <hi>Repute</hi> with the <hi>Wisest</hi> of Persons in all Ages. Yea, and this too, when that Noble <hi>Art</hi> speaks quite different to what the <hi>Libeller</hi> brings it to prove.- I say, these <hi>Monstrous Stories</hi> consider'd, I have been rather too <hi>gentle</hi> and <hi>sparing.</hi>— Yet the Holy Apostle S <hi>Paul,</hi> advises <hi>Titus</hi> to <hi>Rebuke</hi> the <hi>Cretians</hi>) who he says, <hi>are allways Lyars, Evil Beasts, &amp;c.</hi> as this <hi>Libeller) Sharply</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Cuttingly.) That they may be sound in the Faith, <hi>Tit. c.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 12.13.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>EPist. page 3. read <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. June, r. <hi>Ingulph</hi>'s, p. 2. l. 4. r. <hi>hear,</hi> p 8. l. 19. for! r., p. 29. r. <hi>not,</hi> p. 35. l. 8. r. Trigon <hi>saith.</hi> p. 34. l. 20. r. <hi>Conjunctiones,</hi> p. 36. l. 24. r. <hi>Moist, or Intemperate.</hi> Smaller <hi>Errors</hi> are left to the Breast of the Candid <hi>Reader</hi> for Pardon.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:152706:35"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>